2022年12月の
ブロードキャスティングへようこそ
Welcome to JW Broadcasting®
for December 2022!
9月10日 24人の生徒たちが
On September 10th,
24 students reached a milestone
ギレアデ152期を卒業しました
and graduated from the 152nd class of Gilead.
生徒の多くはしばらく前に
招待されていましたが
Many of the students
were initially invited to attend the school,
but they patiently waited
until COVID-19 restrictions eased.
パンデミックに伴う制限が
緩和されるのを待っていました
生徒たちはどうすれば
Now, after five months of intensive study,
5カ月間集中的に学んだことを
生かせるでしょうか
how will they apply their training?
どのように割り当てを
果たせるでしょうか
How can they succeed in their assignments?
兄弟姉妹をどのように
力づけられるでしょうか
And how can they strengthen
their brothers and sisters?
These questions and more are answered
こうした点がギレアデ卒業式で
取り上げられました
in Part 1 of this Gilead graduation program.
では パート1をご覧ください
さあ いよいよこの日が来ました
Well, this day has arrived for you students.
生徒の皆さん 笑顔で今日の
プログラムを楽しみにしておられますね
I see you there smiling
and looking forward to this program.
I’m sure it’s hard for you to believe
that we’ve actually gotten to graduation day.
もう卒業の日を迎えたなんて
信じられない気持ちかもしれません
皆さんはきっと
これからの割り当てのことを考えて
But we also know that you’re very keen
and enthusiastic to get to your assignments,
熱意に燃えていることでしょう
whether you’re going back
to where you came from
元の場所に戻る方も
新しい場所に行く方もです
or you’re going to a new assignment.
この数カ月間 皆さんは
一生懸命勉強しました
Over the last few months,
you’ve learned so much, haven’t you?
You’ve crammed that information
into your mind and heart,
たくさんの情報を学んで
心に取り入れる必要がありましたね
and now you have that ready to implement it
学んださまざまなことを
割り当てられた場所で生かしたいと
思っていることでしょう
when you go to your assignments.
でも 注意しなければ
いけないことがあります
But we need to be careful
not only to be enthusiastic,
keen, and zealous,
熱い心は大切ですが
but also we need to be patient.
焦らないようにしなければなりません
それでこれから
次のテーマでお話ししたいと思います
So we’d like to talk to you
for a few moments about this theme
“Be Enthusiastic but Be Patient” as well.
「熱い心で でも焦らずに！」
Why so?
皆さんはこれから
割り当てられた場所に向かいます
Well, when you go to your assignments
with all this that you’ve learned,
たくさんのことを学んだので
you’re going to be tempted
to try and implement it everywhere.
ぜひ当てはめたいと思うことでしょう
至る所でです
But remember, you’re not going to change
the whole world in one day
でも1日で世界を変えることは
できません
or even the whole branch.
ベテルもです
ありがちなのは 一度に
何でもかんでも行おうとすることです
You see,
it’s so easy to become overwhelmed
if we try to take on too much
all at one time.
でも そんなことをしたら
疲れ切ってしまうでしょう
So that’s why it’s important
to be enthusiastic
ですから熱い心を持つだけでなく
焦らないことが大切です
but also patient.
Our Lord Jesus Christ
was an excellent example of this.
イエス･キリストは
この点で素晴らしい手本です
世界中の人たちは イエスから
すぐにでも教えてもらう必要がありました
When Jesus came into the world,
the whole world needed to hear his message.
でもイエスは エホバの時刻表に従って
And yet, he had to wait some 30 years,
30年ほど待たなければなりませんでした
growing up according to Jehovah’s timetable,
before he started his ministry.
その後 宣教を始めました
So that took patience on his part, didn’t it?
それまで辛抱強く待つ必要がありました
ではイエスは宣教を
どのように行ったでしょうか
But what about when Jesus
started his ministry?
何に力を注いだでしょうか
想像してみてください
What was his focus?
You can imagine him looking around,
当時の世界には しなければ
ならないことがたくさんありました
seeing all the things that needed to be done
in the world at that point.
But let’s turn in our Bibles.
でもイエスはこう言いました
If you turn with me, please,
to Matthew chapter 15
ご一緒にマタイ 15章を
見てみましょう
—Matthew 15:24,
マタイ 15:24です
and here Jesus said to his apostles:
イエスは使徒たちにこう言っています
“I was not sent to anyone
「私は イスラエル国民の迷い出た
羊の所にしか遣わされていません」
except to the lost sheep
of the house of Israel.”
興味深いですね
That’s interesting.
Jesus here mentions
he had a specific, limited assignment.
イエスは 限られた特定の人たちの所に
遣わされていました 誰でしょうか
What was the assignment?
To go “to the lost sheep
of the house of Israel.”
「イスラエル国民の迷い出た羊」です
Now, if you turn back
just a couple of chapters,
少し前のマタイ 10章を開いて
5, 6節を見ると
in chapter 10 of Matthew,
イエスは使徒たちに
こういうことも言っています
you’ll notice in verses 5 and 6
that when Jesus sent out his apostles,
マタイ 10:5, 6です
what did he say to them?
「異国の人々の所に行ってはならず
“Do not go off into the road of the nations,
“and do not enter any Samaritan city;
サマリア人の町に入ってはなりません
“but instead, go continually
いつも イスラエル国民の
迷い出た羊の所に行きなさい」
to the lost sheep of the house of Israel.”
So as Jesus sent out his apostles
イエスはこの時
使徒たちを遣わすに当たって
in this particular instance,
どんなことを指示したでしょうか
what was he reminding them of?
使徒たちにも 限られた
特定の人々の所に行くよう指示しました
He was telling them
that they likewise had a limited assignment,
a specific assignment.
使徒たちは 一度に全ての人々に
伝道するようにとは言われませんでした
They weren’t supposed to try
and do everything all at once
—to go to the Samaritans and to the Gentiles.
「イスラエル国民の迷い出た羊」の所に
行くよう言われたのです
They were to focus
just on “the lost sheep of the house of Israel.”
So when we think about this,
いかがでしょうか この2つの聖句から
どんなことを学べますか
what do we learn from these two verses?
Well, first of all,
もちろん 良い知らせは
世界中の人が聞く必要があります
yes, the whole world
needed to hear the message.
でもイエスはどうしましたか
使徒たちには何を期待しましたか
But what did Jesus do,
and what did he expect of his apostles?
That they would recognize
that they had a specific assignment.
使徒たちが自分たちの割り当てを
しっかり果たすことです
They weren’t to be overwhelmed
ですから 圧倒される必要は
ありませんでした
by trying to think of changing
the whole world at that point.
世界を変える必要はなかったのです
Jesus showed great trust in Jehovah.
イエスはエホバを信頼していました
エホバが良い知らせを伝える対象を
徐々に広げ
He knew that Jehovah
would gradually expand the message
活動を拡大させていくことを
知っていました
and the reach of the message.
And, of course, we realize
that at Pentecost there was an expansion
実際 西暦33年のペンテコステの時
さらに西暦36年にそうなりました
and then in 36 C.E., another expansion.
皆さんとどういう関係があるでしょうか
So, what does that mean for you?
You see, when you return to your assignment
or you go to the new one,
皆さんが元の支部に戻った時
あるいは新しい場所に行った時
there’s going to be
an endless number of possibilities
兄弟姉妹や区域の人たちを
助けるためにできることは
where you can help others
数限りなくあることでしょう
—to stabilize and strengthen everyone.
みんなを安定させ 強めるためです
But if you try to take everything on at once,
でもいっぺんに
全てのことをしようとしたら
you’re going to wear yourself out
自分も疲れますし 多分周りの人たちも
疲れ切ってしまうでしょう
and probably wear out
a whole lot of other people as well.
You know the English idiom
“Don’t bite off more than you can chew.”
よく「かめないほど多くの物を
口に入れるな」と言われます
You see, gradually do the things
that Jehovah has assigned you to do.
エホバからの割り当てを
一つ一つ果たしていくようにしましょう
If you try to be too broad in what you do,
たくさんのことを行おうとして
いっぺんに手を広げると
思ったほど多くのことは行えません
you may end up not accomplishing much at all
except just wearing yourself out.
疲れ切ってしまうだけです
But be patient just as Jesus was,
イエスのように辛抱強い人になりましょう
and recognize that each one of you
will have a specific assignment.
皆さんにはそれぞれ
果たすべき自分の割り当てがあります
それを十分に果たしましょう
And then try to work at that,
trusting that Jehovah will allow
皆さんが周りの人のために
一生懸命頑張っていれば
your good example to benefit others,
その良い影響は徐々に広がっていきます
and gradually the effects of your work
will spread to others.
エホバは必ず後押しをしてくださいます
Now, an example of this is
in the South Pacific,
その良い例が南太平洋です
if I could just tell you about that now.
ちょっとお話しさせてください
その地域に宣教者たちが来た頃
When missionaries arrived
in the South Pacific—
Let’s take, for example,
例えばあなたが
その1人だったとしましょう
you might end up in a country
その地域には
人が住んでいる島が100あります
that has 100 inhabited islands.
Now you’re a new missionary.
宣教者としてやる気満々です
I remember the feeling.
And then you find out
there are only ten islands
でもそのうち エホバの証人が
住んでいるのは10の島だけです
that have Jehovah’s Witnesses on them
ほかの90の島には会衆はありません
—ten islands that have
publishers and congregations.
So there are 90 that don’t.
伝道者もいません
So, what do you think
the normal enthusiastic response is?
熱意に燃えた宣教者だったら
きっとこう思うでしょう
「これは大変だ 船を用意しよう！
すぐに出掛けよう
“Oh, let’s get a boat.
We have to get a boat!
“We must visit all the 90 islands.
90の島全部に行かなきゃ
ああ！今すぐ行って伝道しなきゃ」
Oh, that needs to be done now, immediately!”
でも普通割り当てられるのは
1つの地域の1つの会衆だけです
Well, usually you’re assigned
to one congregation
in one area.
ポイントは何でしょうか
Now, what’s the point?
What normally happens?
もし船を手に入れて
90の島に行ったらどうなるでしょう
Well, you see, if you were to get a boat
(and there’s nothing wrong
with getting a boat
もちろん船で島に行くのは
悪いことではありません
or visiting other islands)
and if that becomes your focus
and you neglect your assignment,
でも自分の割り当てを忘れて
そうしたとしても
90の島で関心を示した人を
十分に助けられるでしょうか
how can you follow up on all the interest
that you may find on those 90 islands?
It’s not just enough
to go and give them some magazines,
島に行って雑誌を渡すだけでは
不十分です
but you need to be there with them,
そこに滞在して人々を教え
会衆をつくらなければなりません
build them up,
and form congregations.
So normally what happens?
でもよくこんなことがあります
Well, it’s amazing to see
missionaries and others
宣教者や他の兄弟姉妹が
比較的大きな町で奉仕しています
who work in maybe larger city areas;
人口が密集している所で
一生懸命に伝道します
they work diligently at their assignments.
ある時 他の島の人が
But then maybe others from different islands
何かの用事で宣教者たちが
奉仕している町にやって来ます
come to visit that city
the missionaries are in,
and they get contacted.
そしてエホバの証人に会い 興味を示し
聖書を学び 島に戻っていきます
They show an interest, they start to study,
and they return to their home islands.
And what happens?
こうして良い知らせが
徐々に島々に広がっていきます
Gradually, the work spreads out
to all these islands.
何を学べるでしょうか
So, what’s the point?
Don’t feel
that you have to take on everything.
何もかもしようとする必要はありません
イエスのように 自分に割り当てられた
ことを十分に行いましょう
Focus as Jesus did
on the limited assignment you have.
But then along the way,
you may be surprised at what happens.
そうしている間に 思いがけないことが
起きるかもしれません
Now, that’s exactly what happened to Jesus.
イエスはまさにそのような経験をしました
もう一度 マタイ 15章を
見てみましょう
Let’s go back to Matthew chapter 15.
イエスはどの区域を
割り当てられていたでしょうか
Remember,
what was the assignment that Jesus had?
In verse 24,
24節にある通り 「イスラエル」です
he mentioned “Israel.”
Now, looking at this map, we see at that time
地図をご覧ください
このグレーの部分がイスラエルです
there was actually a border around that area
これがイエスの割り当てられた区域
だったことになります
that we could say was his territory assignment.
ではイエスはこの言葉を語った時
どこにいたでしょうか
But when Jesus said these words,
where was he?
覚えておられますか
Do you remember?
Let’s look in verse 21:
21節にはこうあります
“Jesus now went into the region
「イエスは⋯⋯
ティルスとシドンの地方に行った」
of Tyre and Sidon.”
So when you look at the map,
ティルスとシドンは
地図のどこにあるでしょうか
where was Tyre and Sidon?
お気付きのように
イエスは区域内にいませんでした
What do you notice?
You see, he wasn’t in his territory.
He was out among the Gentiles.
異国の人々の所にいたのです
なぜでしょうか
Why?
Well, when we look at the parallel account
並行記述のマルコ 7章を見ると
イエスが使徒たちと一緒に
that’s mentioned in Mark chapter 7,
it tells us that Jesus wanted
some time alone with his apostles,
少しリラックスしたいと
思っていたことが分かります
人々が大勢押し寄せてきて
とても忙しかったからです
some downtime
because there were so many crowds;
they were so busy.
Now, I’m sure all of us
can understand that feeling Jesus had.
こういう気持ち
私たちもよく分かりますよね
So he took them out of that general area
それでイエスは 区域の外に
使徒たちを連れ出しました
to this territory
普段伝道していた区域の外に行ったのです
that was beyond what he
would normally preach in
to have some quiet time together.
静かな時間を過ごすためです
どうなったでしょうか
But what happened?
Well, the account tells us
that there was a Syrophoenician woman,
イエスの所に1人の女性がやって来ます
聖句によるとこの女性はギリシャ人で
perhaps (as the study notes help us to see)
from a Greek background
シリアのフェニキアで暮らしていました
as far as her nationality went,
この女性には 邪悪な天使に
取りつかれた小さな娘がいます
but maybe she was a citizen
or an inhabitant of that area,
the Syrophoenician area.
イエスの所に来て
娘を助けてほしいと嘆願します
So this woman approached Jesus,
pleading with him.
もちろん 見た目からして
ユダヤ人ではありません
Now, she didn’t look like a Jewish person.
She probably didn’t even speak Hebrew.
おそらくヘブライ語も
話せなかったでしょう
明らかにイスラエル国民の
迷い出た羊の1人ではありません
She certainly wasn’t in the category
of the lost ones of the house of Israel.
So Jesus,
それでイエスは最初 使徒たちに
initially when she started
to make these efforts to talk to him,
マタイ 15:24に
ある通りのことを言いました
mentioned this to his apostles in verse 24:
「私たちに割り当てられているのは
イスラエル国民です」
‘That’s our assignment.’
But notice that this was a little different
でも聖句をよく見ると
この女性はイエスについて
in the sense that this woman
showed an appreciation for who Jesus was.
ある程度知っていたことが分かります
22節を見ると女性はこう言っています
Notice in verse 22, she said:
“Have mercy on me, Lord, Son of David.”
「主よ ダビデの子よ
憐れみをお掛けください」
Now, here’s a Gentile woman.
異国の女性です
普通ならダビデのことを
よく知らないでしょう
Should she really know who David was?
And by saying “Son of David,”
でもイエスを「ダビデの子」と
呼んでいます
as the study note indicates,
perhaps she was showing faith
注釈にある通り
イエスをメシアと認めていたのでしょう
in the fact that Jesus is the Messiah.
イエスに信仰を持っていたようです
フェニキアの他の人たちとは
違っていました
So she wasn’t
your average Syrophoenician person.
What did Jesus do?
イエスはどうしたでしょうか
女性の信仰を少し試しました
Well, he tested her a little.
He did emphasize
the fact that in a household
こう言います 「普通父親はまず家族
子供たちに食べ物を与えます
you first of all
feed the children, the family,
and then the little dogs get fed afterward.
それから小犬に食べ物を与えます」
And perhaps he was playing on words there.
面白い言い方をしていますね
It’s interesting.
イエスがこの女性に
何語で話したのかは分かりません
We’re not sure
what language Jesus was speaking to her.
でも「ものみの塔」によると
イエスはギリシャ語を理解し
The Watchtower{
perhaps did understand Greek
and use it at times.
時折使っていたようです
使徒たちもギリシャ語を理解しました
Why, his apostles
obviously understood some Greek.
聖書の幾つかの書を
ギリシャ語で書きました
They wrote some of the books of the Bible
in Greek.
But whatever the case,
the record of this is written
いずれにしても 神の導きを受けて
書かれたこのギリシャ語の記録で
—the inspired record—
in Greek,
「小犬」という表現が使われています
and it uses this term “little dogs.”
女性を侮辱していたわけではありません
Was that offensive?
No.
As it’s mentioned,
it was an affectionate term
これはかわいいペットに使うような
愛情のこもった表現です
like saying “puppies” or “pets.”
So whatever the case,
いずれにしても イエスは
笑顔を浮かべて
優しく話し掛けたのでしょう
he must have looked very friendly,
perhaps had a smile on his face,
女性の反応からそれが分かります
because she was not deterred.
What was Jesus’ reaction?
イエスはどうしたでしょうか
自分に割り当てられた区域については
分かっていましたが
Well, he acknowledged
his territory, his assignment.
28節でこう言っています
But then in verse 28, he said,
“O woman, great is your faith;
「素晴らしい信仰です！
let it happen to you as you wish.”
あなたの願う通りのことが
起きますように」
イエスがユダヤ人ではない人に
Is this the only time
that Jesus did something like this
このように接した例は
ほかにもあるでしょうか
for a non-Jewish person?
Remember in John chapter 4,
ヨハネ 4章に書かれています
not only do we have this case
of the Syrophoenician woman,
シリアのフェニキアで会った
先ほどの女性だけでなく
but in John chapter 4,
we’re told about the Samaritan woman.
ヨハネ 4章にあるように
サマリアの女性にも親切に接しました
This non-Jewish person was witnessed to,
ユダヤ人ではないこの女性に伝道しました
and then even members of her village
その女性の村の人たちも
イエスがメシアであると信じました
accepted Jesus as the Messiah.
And then what about the Roman army officer
イエスはローマの士官のことも助けました
that Jesus was able to help?
その士官について イスラエルの中でも
And Jesus mentioned
that he hadn’t even seen
これほどの信仰を見たことがない と
さえ言いました
that type of faith in all of Israel.
こうした例から何を学べるでしょうか
So, what lesson do we learn from this?
イエスは自分の割り当てに力を注ぎました
Well, Jesus focused on his assignment.
He always acknowledged
what he was assigned to do.
自分の割り当てが何かを
いつも意識していました
But when opportunities came up along the way
でもその間 機会が訪れた時には
to help those
who weren’t necessarily in his assignment,
割り当てられた対象ではない
人たちも助けました
he still gave them some help
困っている誠実な人たちを
放っておくことはできなかったのです
because they were genuine persons
who needed help.
Yes, although Jesus realized
it wasn’t yet the time to expand the work,
イエスは活動の範囲を広げるべき時では
ないことを知っていましたが
それでもそういう人を喜んで助けました
he was willing to reach out
to these ones as well.
So, what’s the lesson for all of us?
私たちみんなが学べる点は何でしょうか
Well, when you go to your assignments,
you will have specific assignments.
皆さんはそれぞれの場所で
特定の割り当てを受けるでしょう
Now, if it’s in a Bethel or in the field,
ベテルであれ野外であれ
割り当てられた仕事ははっきりしています
you’ll know what your assignment is.
So don’t start looking
at all the other assignments that are around
ですから いろいろなことに
手を出そうとする必要はありません
and how you can help them
and what you need to do
「どうやって助けよう 何をしてあげよう
and say, “Oh, why don’t they change?”
ああ 何とかしなきゃ」
I mean, you’ve changed a lot
in the last few months;
皆さんとは違って周りの人たちは
そんなに変化していません
but remember, they haven’t.
And they survived without you.
皆さんがいなくても大丈夫でした
それで 大切なのは
So, what’s the key?
与えられた仕事に集中することです
Focus on your assignment.
Be zealous, be enthusiastic,
熱い心を持つとともに
but also be patient.
焦らないようにしましょう
Yes, have trust in Jehovah
ですから まずは自分に割り当てられた
仕事を一生懸命に行いましょう
that if you focus on your assignment,
you work hard,
そして機会が訪れたら
できることをしましょう
you take up whatever opportunities
come your way along the way,
then you can be sure you will be blessed
そうすればエホバが支えてくれます
熱い心で でも焦らずに頑張りましょう
because you’re enthusiastic but also patient.
Well, now with those thoughts in mind,
こうした点を考えながら
これからのプログラムを楽しみましょう
we have a very interesting program
ahead of us.
最初に話してくださるのは
First up, we have Brother Kenneth Cook,
a member of the Governing Body.
統治体のケニス･クック兄弟です
And Brother Cook
is going to talk to you on the theme
兄弟の話の主題は
「エホバに喜ばれるために
必要な3つのこと」です
“Follow the Steps That Lead to Blessings.”
お願いします
Brother Cook, please.
To begin, I’d like to share
a personal experience with you.
まず 自分の経験を
少しお話ししたいと思います
統治体の成員としての
任命を知らされた時
When I was told that I was appointed to be
a member of the Governing Body,
それを伝えてくれた兄弟たちの
1人がこう言いました
one of the brothers who informed me said:
「統治体に割り当てられると
責任がぐっと重くなります
“With this assignment, you’ll experience
“a great increase in responsibility.
でもそれとともに エホバの聖なる力の
助けもぐっと増えます
“But you’ll also see a corresponding increase
“in Jehovah’s spirit to help you.
It will not be too much for you.”
だから大丈夫ですよ」
その言葉を聞いて
とても安心したのを覚えています
Well, those words were very,
very reassuring to me.
And the fact is that all of us
実際私たち全ては
どんな立場で奉仕しているとしても
(no matter who we are)
serving Jehovah faithfully
エホバに頼ることが大切です
must rely on his help
そうすれば良い結果になります
to succeed in serving him.
では どのようにエホバに
頼ればいいのでしょうか
Now, how do we show this
and receive his help?
幾つもありますが
この話では3つ取り上げます
There are a number of ways.
We’re going to focus on three of them.
They are these: Follow direction, show faith,
指示に従うこと 信仰を示すこと
and use common sense,
or the thinking ability,
そして思考力を使って
良い判断をすることです
that Jehovah has given to us.
エホバから与えられた能力です
So let’s consider the first step.
まず1つ目です
エホバのシンプルで明快な
指示に従いさえすれば
Sometimes all that’s required
to receive Jehovah’s blessing on our work
エホバに喜ばれ
良い結果になることがあります
is to follow simple, clear direction.
聖書中の例を見てみましょう
Now, here’s a Bible example of that.
It’s found in Mark chapter 14
マルコ 14章です
—Mark chapter 14.
マルコ 14章
Now, you’ll recall from this account
神の子イエスは弟子の2人に
that God’s Son directed two of his disciples
過ぎ越しのためにエルサレムに行って
to go into Jerusalem and to prepare a large,
整った大きな階上の部屋を
準備するよう指示しました
furnished upper room for the Passover.
His directions were specific.
指示は具体的でした
For instance, Jesus said that they would meet
例えば イエスは弟子たちに
‘a man carrying a large, earthenware jar,
水がめを運んでいる男の人に会ったら
付いていくように と言いました
and they were to follow him.’
And then starting in verse 14,
Jesus added this,
また 14節以降でこうも言っています
he said: “Wherever he goes inside,
say to the master of the house,
「『その人がどこに入っていっても
家の主人にこう言いなさい
“‘The Teacher says: “Where is the guest room
「先生が 『弟子たちと
過ぎ越しの食事ができる客室は
“where I may eat
the Passover with my disciples?”’
どこでしょうか』と言っています」
“And he will show you a large upper room,
furnished and ready.
そうすると 整った大きな
階上の部屋を見せてくれます
“Prepare it for us there.
そこで準備をしなさい』
それで弟子たちは出ていった
“So the disciples went out,
and they entered the city
“and found it just as he said to them,
町に入ると イエスが言った通りになり
過ぎ越しの準備をした」
and they prepared for the Passover.”
このように指示は明快でした
So the directions were simple, right?
どこへ行くか 誰に付いていくか
They were told where they should go,
who they should follow,
what they were to say,
何と言うか 何をするかを指示しました
and what they were to do.
2人の弟子たちは指示にすぐ従いました
And the two disciples promptly followed
that direction,
and of course, their obedience
brought many blessings, as we know.
従って良い結果になりました
ご存じの通りです
Well, what practical lesson
can you draw from this?
このことから何を学べるでしょうか
与えられるシンプルで明快な指示に
The lesson: Sometimes all that is needed
in serving Jehovah
従いさえすればよい
場合がある ということです
is to follow simple, clear direction.
You’ll have many opportunities to do so
in your assignments.
皆さんが奉仕するときにも
そういうケースはたくさんあるでしょう
Follow clear direction,
and look for Jehovah’s blessing on it.
明快な指示に従い
エホバの導きや助けを求めましょう
でも 指示に従う以上のことを
行う必要がある場合があるでしょう
But now, on the other hand,
you might be asked to care for something
that’s far more involved than that.
For example, what if you’re asked
to assist someone
例えば なかなか一筋縄では
いかないような人を援助するよう
who’s known to be difficult to deal with?
依頼されるかもしれません
あるいは 他の人たちが
解決できなかった問題を扱うよう
Or you’re asked
to care for a work-related problem
that others have not been able to solve.
頼まれるかもしれません
ギレアデで訓練を受けたということで
そういう依頼を受けます
You’re the one selected
because you’ve had the training.
そんなとき 何が役立つでしょうか
In such a case, what will help you?
強い信仰です これが2つ目です
Your strong faith—the next step.
The fact is that at times we need to show
added faith to fulfill our assignments.
難しい割り当てを受けたときには
いっそう強い信仰が必要です
True?
アナニアの例を考えましょう
アナニアは信仰を持っていました
Consider the example of Ananias.
Now, he too was a man of faith,
but he faced a challenge
that required even more of him,
でもある時 もっと信仰が
必要になりました
and we read about it in Acts chapter 9.
使徒 9章を見てみましょう
10節からです
We’ll begin with verse 10
—Acts 9:10—
使徒 9:10
「ダマスカスには
アナニアという弟子がいた
it says: “There was a disciple
named Ananias in Damascus,
幻の中で主が 『アナニア！』と呼ぶと
アナニアは言った
“and the Lord said to him in a vision:
‘Ananias!’
“He said: ‘Here I am, Lord.’
『主よ 何でしょうか』 主は言った
『さあ 「真っすぐ」という通りに行き
サウロという人を捜しなさい
“The Lord said to him:
‘Get up, go to the street called Straight,
“‘and look for a man named Saul, from Tarsus,
タルソス出身で ユダの家にいます
今サウロは祈っています
“‘at the house of Judas.
“‘For look! he is praying,
サウロは幻の中で
アナニアという人が入ってきて
“‘and in a vision he has seen
a man named Ananias
目が見えるように手を置いて
くれるのを見ました』
“come in and lay his hands on him
so that he may recover sight.’
アナニアは答えた 『主よ
“But Ananias answered: ‘Lord,
私は多くの人から
この男について聞いています
“‘I have heard from many about this man,
エルサレムにいる聖なる人たちに
いろいろと危害を加えたとのことです
“‘about all the harm he did
to your holy ones in Jerusalem.
ここでは あなたの名を呼ぶ人を
皆捕らえようとして
“‘And here he has authority
from the chief priests
祭司長たちから権限を受けています』
“to arrest all those calling on your name.’
しかし主は言った 『行きなさい
“But the Lord said to him:
‘Go! because this man
この人は私が選んだ器であり
異国の人々に
“‘is a chosen vessel to me
to bear my name to the nations
また王たちやイスラエルの民に
私の名を知らせるからです
“‘as well as to kings and the sons of Israel.
私は彼に 私の名のために
“‘For I will show him plainly how many things
どれほど多くの苦しみを受けなければ
ならないかをはっきり示します』」
he must suffer for my name.’”
Well, the direction was clear.
明快な指示です
アナニアはどこに行くべきでしたか
「真っすぐ」という通りです
Where should Ananias go?
To the street called Straight.
誰を捜しますか
サウロという人です
Who was he looking for?
A man named Saul.
サウロは誰の家にいますか ユダです
What house is he in?
The house of Judas.
Ananias was even told what Saul was doing.
アナニアは サウロが何を
しているのかを知らされました
祈っています
He was praying.
サウロを見つけたら何をすべきですか
Then Ananias was told what he should do.
He was to lay his hands on him
so that he would recover sight.
サウロに手を置いて サウロの目が
見えるようにすることです
シンプルな指示ですね
あとはイエスがやってくれます
Simple, right?
Jesus would do the rest.
What a great example
of giving clear direction!
イエスがアナニアに与えた指示は
本当に明快でした
でも アナニアには強い信仰が
求められました
But here is where Ananias
needed to stir up more faith.
サウロは エルサレムの聖なる人たちを
厳しく迫害していた人です
The man he was to visit
had severely persecuted
the holy ones in Jerusalem.
アナニアはイエスに対し
And speaking to the Lord, Ananias added
サウロが「あなたの名を呼ぶ人を
皆捕らえようとして
that this man
“has authority from the chief priests
祭司長たちから権限を受けて
います」とも言っています
to arrest all those calling on your name.”
そんなこと イエスは言われなくても
分かってますよね？
Well, talk about stating
the obvious to Jesus.
いずれにしてもアナニアは
イエスからこの指示を受けた時
The point is that Ananias had a moment
where he was overwhelmed
by the weight of the assignment.
難し過ぎると感じました
That’s just what happened.
必要だったのは信仰です
What would help him?
More faith.
And Jesus knew how to draw it up
in that dear man.
イエスはアナニアの信仰を強めました
Look again at Jesus’ reply.
何と言ったでしょうか
行くようにともう一度指示します
He simply restated his command: “Go.”
Then Jesus said that “this man
is a chosen vessel to me
さらにこう言います
「この人は私が選んだ器であり
異国の人々に また王たちや
イスラエルの民に
“to bear my name to the nations
as well as to kings and the sons of Israel.”
私の名を知らせるからです」
Now, Jesus added something there, didn’t he?
イエスはさらに詳しく説明していますね
その後どうなるかについて言っています
He pointed to the future.
What was he doing?
サウロがこれから果たす
役割を説明しました
He was helping Ananias to look ahead, see.
それを聞いたアナニアは
強い信仰を示すことができました
And doing this evidently prompted Ananias
to show even more faith,
which is what he needed.
そのことはサウロに言った
言葉から分かります
How do we know this?
17節をご覧ください
Well, look at what he said to Saul.
On meeting Saul, verse 17 tells us
アナニアはサウロに会った時
サウロに「兄弟」と呼び掛けました
that Ananias called him “brother.”
His initial hesitation had changed
アナニアは信仰が強まったので
into putting his full faith and trust
ためらいの気持ちがなくなり
イエスの指示に従いました
in Jesus’ direction.
私たちもこれから難しい問題を
扱う必要があるでしょう
Well, like Ananias,
as you face challenges in the future
(and they will come;
they come upon all of us),
そんなとき エホバが私たちに
必要なものを与えてくれる という
have strong faith
that Jehovah sees what is needed,
強い信仰を持ちましょう
エホバもイエスも
私たちを助けてくれます
and he and his dear Son will help you.
広い視野を持ちましょう
Keep the big picture in mind,
頑張ればエホバは支えてくれます
and look to the blessings ahead
for your hard work.
強い信仰を示せば
エホバは必ず報いてくれます
Jehovah will always bless
your strong faith in him.
Well, so far we’ve looked at the need
to follow clear direction
明確な指示に従うこと
強い信仰を示すことについて考えました
and to show strong faith.
Now we’re going to add another step:
では もう1つの点です
思考力を使って良い判断をすることです
Use common sense, or thinking ability.
エリヤについて考えましょう
Our Bible example—Elijah.
In this account,
Elijah has traveled to Zarephath,
エリヤがフェニキアの海沿いの町
ザレパテに行った時のことです
a Phoenician coastal town.
なぜそこに行ったのでしょうか
What was his business there?
長い間干ばつが生じていたので
Well, the land was
in the grip of a long drought,
エホバはその町にいるある人を通して
エリヤを助けることにしたのです
and Jehovah would help his prophet
by means of someone in that town.
エホバはエリヤに言いました
Elijah was told: “Look!
「私はそこで1人のやもめに命じて
あなたに食べ物を与えさせる」
I will command a widow there
to supply you with food.”
It appears that he gave no other details
about the widow than that.
やもめについてそれ以上の
情報はありません
So how would Elijah find her?
どうやって見つけたらいいのでしょう
Would Elijah look for the wealthiest widow
to care for his needs?
世話をしてくれる裕福なやもめを
探せばいいのでしょうか
それとも 信仰を抱いて思考力を使い
良い判断をするでしょうか
Or would he use common sense
and thinking ability along with his faith?
エリヤはどうするでしょう
列王第一 17章を見てみましょう
Let’s see what Elijah does
at 1 Kings chapter 17.
10節を読んでみます
列王第一 17:10
And we’re going to read verse 10
—First Kings 17:10,
it says: “So he [Elijah]
rose up and went to Zarephath.
「そこでエリヤは出発し
ザレパテに行った
“When he came to the entrance of the city,
町の入り口に来ると
1人のやもめが薪を拾っていた
“there was a widow gathering pieces of wood.
“So he called to her and said:
エリヤは女性に声を掛け 言った
‘Please, bring me a little water in a cup
so that I may drink.’”
『どうか水を少し持ってきて
飲ませてください』」
エリヤは何をしましたか
So then what did Elijah do?
Evidently, he approached
the very first widow he met.
おそらく 最初に会ったやもめに
声を掛けたのでしょう
裕福ではなく 貧しいやもめでした
And she was not a wealthy widow,
but a poor one.
エリヤは町の入口に来ただけで
町の中に入ってもいませんでした
In fact, it says Elijah had not yet passed
beyond the entrance of the city.
エリヤについてどんなことが
分かりますか
What does this tell us about Elijah?
1つ目に エリヤは先入観を抱かずに
エホバの指示に従いました
First, he showed no prejudice
in following through on Jehovah’s direction,
did he?
And second, he added thinking ability
2つ目に 指示に従い
信仰を示しただけでなく
to his obedience and faith.
思考力を使いました
どのようにでしょうか
How so?
エリヤはよく考えて
最初に会ったやもめが
Well, common sense would tell him
to show his faith
神が選んだ人かどうかを
見極めようとしたのです
and start looking
with the very first widow he met.
Elijah obviously had confidence
どのやもめかをエホバがはっきり
分からせてくれると確信していました
that Jehovah would make his choice clear.
従順 信仰 判断力を示したので
His obedience, faith, and good sense
were rewarded
because that widow was Jehovah’s choice.
エホバが選んだやもめに
会うことができました
もちろん 聖なる力の助けもありました
Now, surely holy spirit guided Elijah,
でもエリヤは 神の指示に
ただ従っただけでなく
but we can’t ignore
the faith and clear thinking ability
that Elijah developed
as he obediently did God’s will.
信仰を示し 思考力を使いました
After all, prior to that widow,
Jehovah used birds
それ以前にも エホバは鳥を使って
エリヤに食べ物を与えました
to carry food to his prophet.
ですから 貧しいやもめを
使うこともできるはずです
Surely Jehovah
could use a poor widow as well.
What’s the lesson for you and for all of us?
この例からどんなことを
学べるでしょうか
Sometimes we’re given much to go on
何かの割り当てを受けるとき
詳しい指示が与えられることもあります
when we receive an assignment
でも 大まかな指示しか
与えられないこともあります
and, at other times, frankly,
maybe not so much.
そのような場合には 信仰を示し
思考力を使いましょう
In such a case,
our faith and clear thinking ability
remind us to trust in Jehovah
エホバに頼り
エホバの望むことを行いながら
and to look for his guidance
as we go forward in doing his will.
導きを求めましょう
Jehovah will always help you dear friends
at the right time.
エホバはいつも ちょうど良い時に
皆さんを助けてくださいます
ではこれからも 指示にすぐ従い
So then, as our examples show, promptly obey,
show strong faith,
and use common sense and thinking ability
強い信仰を示し 思考力を十分に使って
天のお父さんエホバに
仕えていきましょう
in our service to our dear heavenly Father.
こうした点を心に留めておくことは
Remembering such lessons will help you
as you support Jehovah’s work
それぞれの支部での割り当てを
果たしていく助けになるでしょう
in your respective branches.
Jehovah gives power beyond what is normal
エホバはご自分に頼る人全てに
普通を超えた力を与えます
to those who rely on him
今日学んだ3つの点を実践すれば
and follow the steps that lead to blessings.
エホバは皆さんの努力を喜び
支えてくれるでしょう
And we are confident
that this will always be true of you.
Thank you very much, Brother Cook.
クック兄弟 ありがとうございました
You clearly helped us to see
the steps that are needed
エホバに喜ばれるために何が必要かを
学ぶことができました
for us to gain blessings.
Well, now our next speaker on the program
次に話してくださるのは
人事委員会の援助者
ジェフリー･ウィンダー兄弟です
is Brother Jeffrey Winder,
who is a helper to the Personnel Committee.
兄弟はとても興味深い主題で
話してくださいます
And Brother Winder is going to discuss
with us this very interesting question,
「どこまで近づけますか」です
“How Close Can You Be?”
生徒の皆さんは
この質問にどう答えますか
How would you students answer this question:
Do you feel closer to Jehovah now
ギレアデのトレーニングを
受ける前と比べて
エホバとの距離がいっそう
縮まったと感じますか
than you did
before your Gilead training began?
皆さん 「はい そう感じます」と
大きな声で答えるでしょう
The answer is a resounding yes, isn’t it?
これまでのギレアデ卒業生は
こんなことを言っています
Maybe you can relate to these comments
of graduates of past classes of Gilead.
皆さんも同じように
感じていると思います
One brother said: “Absolutely, yes!
ある兄弟はこう言っています
「もちろんです 神と共に歩む
というのがどういうことなのか
“I believe I now experience more fully
“what it means to walk with God
いっそうよく分かるようになりました
“and know and rely upon him
as a close Friend,
今エホバは私にとって 頼れる親友です
単に祈りを捧げる
遠い存在ではありません」
not merely someone
I turn and look up to in prayer.”
ある姉妹はこう言っています
A sister said:
“Gilead definitely drew me closer to Jehovah.
「ギレアデのおかげで
エホバにもっと近づけました
“The way we studied the Scriptures
with intensity
聖書を深く掘り下げて学んで
聖書がエホバからの自分に対する
手紙だという実感が深まりました」
truly made me feel like the Bible
was a letter Jehovah wrote to me.”
別の兄弟のコメントです
Another brother said:
“Jehovah communicated with such clarity,
「エホバの気持ちが
はっきり伝わってきたので
エホバがもっとリアルな
存在になりました
“which made it real and personal.
“It made me feel closer to Jehovah
than ever before,
これまでにないほど エホバを
身近に感じています
この気持ちを忘れることは
決してないでしょう」
and that feeling will never be forgotten.”
Well, unquestionably,
your deep study of God’s Word during Gilead
皆さんもギレアデで聖書を深く学んで
エホバにいっそう近づけたに
違いありません
drew you closer to Jehovah.
ではお尋ねします
But here’s the question,
エホバにどこまで近づけますか
How close can you be?
How close
can your relationship with Jehovah get?
絆をどこまで強められるでしょうか
聖書を5カ月間深く学んで
You saw it leap forward in five months
of deep Bible study, but is there a limit?
エホバとの距離が
ぐっと縮まったと思いますが
ここまでという限界はあるのでしょうか
Is there more?
Will you ever get done?
2つの点を取り上げて考えてみましょう
Consider two points
that answer that question.
The first one is found
in the book of James chapter 4,
1つ目の点はヤコブ 4章にあります
8節の前半をご一緒に読んでみましょう
and let’s read together
the first part of verse 8.
読みながら次の点を考えてください
And let’s read it with that question in mind:
Is there any limit to how close
our relationship with Jehovah could be?
ここまでしかエホバに近づけない
という限界があるのかどうかです
ヤコブ 4:8
James 4:8 says:
「神に近づいてください
“Draw close to God,
そうすれば 神は
近づいてくださいます」
and he will draw close to you.”
近づける限界はあるのでしょうか
So is there any limit indicated here?
Well, it is true that in English
this phrase to “draw close to” someone
普通「近づく」という言葉は
誰かに文字通り近づくときに使います
could be applied in a physical sense
誰かのそばに行くという意味です
—actually standing next to someone.
And in that case, there is a limit.
その場合 限度があります
くっついたらそれ以上行けません
You can only stand so close to someone.
でもこの聖句の近づくというのは
そういう意味ではありません
But that’s not really the sense of James 4:8,
is it?
どういう意味でしょうか
Rather, it’s in this sense:
When we talk about our close friends,
自分にとって身近な友達というのは
we’re not talking about those
that are nearest in proximity.
実際に近い距離にいる
友達のことではありません
親しい友達 強い絆で
結ばれた友達のことです
We’re talking
about the depth of our relationship,
the closeness of our friendship.
And so then to “draw close to God” then means
ですから 「神に近づく」というのは
神との関係を強め
to strengthen our relationship,
strengthen our friendship, with him.
友情を深めるということです
聖句にはその絆の強さには
And then looking at the verse,
does it appear that there’s any limit
限度があるというようなことが
書かれているでしょうか
to how close that relationship can get?
The implication is that as long
as we keep drawing close to Jehovah,
いいえ 私たちが神に近づく
努力を続ければ
神も近づき続けてくださいます
then he’ll keep drawing close to us.
では2つ目の点を考えましょう
And that takes us to our second point,
and that is the real life example
of God’s Son,
神の子イエスから学ぶことができます
because Jesus drew close to Jehovah.
イエスは神に近づきました
エホバから教えられました
Clearly, he was taught by Jehovah.
人間になる前のイエスについて
イザヤ 50:4にはこうあります
Remember Isaiah 50:4,
regarding Jesus’ prehuman existence,
where he said:
「神は毎朝 私を目覚めさせてくださり
“He awakens me morning by morning;
he awakens my ear
to listen like the taught ones.”
私が生徒のように耳を澄まして
聞けるようにしてくださる」
Does that sound a bit
like your Gilead training?
ギレアデにちょっと似ていますね
神は毎朝 生徒の皆さんを
教えてくれました
‘Morning by morning
Jehovah was awakening your ear.’
でもイエスが教えられた期間は
5カ月だけではありません
Yet, Jesus wasn’t instructed by Jehovah
for five months;
he was instructed for billions of years.
それよりはるかに長い間
教えられました
And during all that time,
その間ずっと父エホバとの
絆が強まり続けました
his relationship with his Father
continued to grow and deepen.
友情が深まっていったのです
私たちはどうでしょうか
So, then, we put it all together.
You saw your relationship with Jehovah
grow significantly
皆さんは5カ月間 聖書を深く学んで
エホバとの友情がぐっと深まりました
in five months of deep Bible study.
でもヤコブ 4:8は 神に
近づき続けるよう勧めています
James 4:8 encourages us
to just keep drawing close to Jehovah.
イエスは非常に長い間そうし続けました
And Jesus did so for billions of years,
and look at how close
his relationship with Jehovah is.
その結果 エホバと
とても親しくなれました
では先ほどの質問です
So, then, what’s the answer?
エホバにどこまで
近づくことができますか
How close can you be to Jehovah?
エホバとの友情はいつまでも
どこまでも深めていくことができます
The potential for your relationship
with Jehovah to deepen
is endless.
考えれば考えるほど 素晴らしいですね
Well, that’s just wonderful to contemplate,
isn’t it?
But let’s make some application
でももう少し具体的に考えましょう
because this really becomes
a very important overall lesson
これはギレアデで学んだ
全てのことに関わる
that you take with you
from your Gilead experience:
とても大切なことだからです
聖書を深く学ぶことがエホバとの
関係にどう影響するかということです
That is how your deep Bible study
affected your relationship with Jehovah.
And one of the reasons
why this is such an important lesson
この点が非常に大切といえるのは
なぜでしょうか
is because your success in your assignment
皆さんが割り当てを
十分に果たせるかどうかは
is directly connected to the depth
of your relationship with Jehovah.
エホバとの絆がどれほど深いかに
懸かっているからです
皆さんが割り当てを
十分に果たせるかどうかは
Your success in your assignment
is directly connected to the depth
of your relationship with Jehovah.
エホバとの絆の深さに懸かっています
なぜそういえるでしょうか
Now, why can we say that?
そのことは 聖書を学んで
エホバに近づくと
It’s because of what takes place
when we draw close to Jehovah
through a study of his Word.
どうなるか ということを
考えると分かります
Turn with me, please,
to the book of Psalms,
ご一緒に「詩編」を見てみましょう
and we’ll read the 25th Psalm
詩編 25:4です
in verse 4
25:4 こうあります
—Psalm 25:4.
It says:
“Make me know your ways, O Jehovah;
「エホバ あなたの道を
知らせてください
その道をどう歩むべきかを
教えてください」
teach me your paths.”
This is what’s happening
when we study God’s Word, isn’t it?
神の言葉を学ぶと
こうなるのではないでしょうか
We are coming to know Jehovah God’s ways.
エホバの道が分かるようになります
The Watchtower{
「ものみの塔」にはこうあります
It said: “As we get a deeper
and deeper understanding of God’s Word,
「神の言葉に対する理解が深まるにつれ
神の考え方が自分の中に浸透します」
we become imbued
with God’s way of thinking.”
「神の考え方が自分の中に浸透します」
“We become imbued
with God’s way of thinking.”
The dictionary said that the word
辞書によると 「浸透」するとは
“imbue implies the introduction of a quality
あるものが全体に行き渡ること
that fills and permeates the whole being,”
染み込むこと 染み通ることを
意味します
例えば 染料が布に
染み込んでいく場合などです
so like dyeing a garment or leavening bread.
ですから 神の考え方が
浸透するというのは
But here we’re talking
about being imbued with God’s thinking,
that maybe God’s thinking
would fill and permeate our whole being.
神の考え方が私たちの中に
染み渡るということです
そんなことが可能なのでしょうか
Is that possible?
Think back to the example of Jesus.
イエスの例を思い出してみましょう
As we discussed,
Jesus drew close to Jehovah.
イエスは非常に長い期間にわたって
エホバに近づき
エホバに教えられました
He was taught by Jehovah
for billions of years.
And what was happening
during that whole time?
その間 何が生じていたでしょうか
He was being imbued
with Jehovah God’s thinking.
エホバの考え方がイエスの中に
浸透していきました
それでイエスは地上にいた時
And it so permeated him
that when he was on earth,
ヨハネ 14:9にある通り
こう言いました
he could say at John 14:9:
“Whoever has seen me
has seen the Father also.”
「私を見た人は 父をも見たのです」
So in other words,
everything that Jesus said,
ですから イエスが地上にいた時に
話したり行ったりしたことは全て
everything that he did while on earth
in every situation,
あたかもエホバがそこにいて
well, we could imagine Jehovah
doing and saying those very things.
話したり行ったり
しているかのようでした
それで 皆さんがエホバとの友情を育て
And that is why
the success of your assignment
is directly connected to the depth
of your relationship with Jehovah.
エホバに見習うなら 割り当てられた
仕事を十分に果たせます
聖書をよく学んで
エホバにいっそう近づき
The more you draw close to Jehovah
through a study of his Word,
エホバの考え方を自分の中に
いっそう浸透させるなら
then the more you are imbued
with his thinking
and the more then you will do, or act,
私たちの話すことや行うことは
and say things as Jehovah would.
いっそうエホバに近づくことになります
どんな結果になるでしょうか
And so how does this play out?
Well, in your assignment,
皆さんはこれから
if you have the privilege
to contribute to significant decisions
多くの人に影響を与える大切な
決定を下すことになるかもしれません
that will affect others in your department
部門や支部や野外の兄弟姉妹にです
or at the branch or in the field even,
そのようなとき エホバの考えに合わせ
my, you want to be guided
by Jehovah’s thinking, don’t you?
エホバの望む通りに行いたいと
思うのではないでしょうか
You want to do things as he would do them.
Well, the closer you are to Jehovah,
the deeper that relationship is,
エホバに近づけば近づくほど
エホバとの絆が強ければ強いほど
the more your decisions will mirror his.
エホバに喜ばれる決定ができます
もちろん仲間を強め
安定させるというのは
But, of course, we know
strengthening and stabilizing others
isn’t always done
in big, grand gestures like that
必ずしも大きな決定を下したり
—big decisions,
new organizational arrangements.
新しい取り決めを作ったり
することではありません
Quite often it’s the day-to-day interactions
with others
むしろ 兄弟姉妹と普段接する時に
励ます機会がたくさんあります
that really encourage them.
実際 聖書を見るとイエスが
周りの人と交わした親しい会話や
And isn’t it true that we learn so much
from those intimate conversations
that Jesus had with others,
ちょっとしたやり取りのことが
書かれていますが
or seemingly incidental interactions
that he had with others,
そういう記録を読むと たくさんのことを
学べるのではないでしょうか
that the Bible records?
皆さんも同じようにして
仲間を力づけられます
Well, you will strengthen others
in similar ways.
For example,
例えば皆さんが 服装とか
身だしなみなど
when you are guided
by Jehovah’s thinking in personal matters,
個人的な事柄でもエホバの考えに
合わせようとしているなら
such as in your choice of dress and grooming,
それを見る人たちも個人的な事柄で
well, others will certainly notice that
and that will strengthen their resolve
エホバに喜ばれる決定をしよう
という気持ちが強まります
to make good decisions
in these personal areas.
皆さんが時間の使い方の面でも
エホバの考えに合わせているなら
When you are guided by Jehovah’s thinking
in the use of your time,
as busy as you will be
周りの人たちはそれに気付きます
—when the friends see you in the ministry,
伝道や集会や与えられた仕事に
打ち込んでいるなら それを見る人は
at the meetings,
working hard in your assignment—
they will take notice of that
自分もエホバへの奉仕を第一に
しようという決意が強まるでしょう
and that will strengthen their resolve
to make good priorities in their life.
では会話をポジティブな方向に
持っていくようにしましょう
Every time you steer
a negative conversation to the positive,
every time you show
a willingness to do humble tasks,
目立たない仕事を進んで行いましょう
判断を下す前に時間を取って
双方の意見を聞くようにしましょう
every time you take the time
to get the other side of the story
before rendering judgment
—yes, in all these areas of your daily life,
そのように生活のあらゆる
シーンでエホバに近づき
you give evidence
that you have drawn close to Jehovah,
エホバの考え方を自分の中に浸透させ
you have been imbued with his thinking,
エホバのように行動していることを
明らかにするなら
and you are acting as Jehovah would.
And in that case,
皆さんは兄弟姉妹を強め
you absolutely will strengthen and stabilize
your brothers!
安定させることができます
Well, we love you
私たちはエホバとの友情を育てている
皆さんを愛しています
for your relationship with Jehovah.
And we encourage you
to take this lesson of Gilead with you
皆さんはギレアデで
大切なことを学びました
聖書を深く学んで
エホバとの絆が強まりました
—the effect that your deep Bible study
had on your relationship with Jehovah—
そしてこれからも絆を強める
必要があることを学びました
and keep drawing close to him.
The potential is endless,
強めれば強めるほど エホバに
喜ばれることを行えるでしょう
and this is what will ensure your success.
Well, may the rich blessing of Jehovah,
your Friend, be with you
ギレアデで受けた訓練を生かして
割り当てを果たす皆さんを
as you use your Gilead training
in the assignments he has given you.
友であるエホバが豊かに
祝福してくださいますように
Well, I’m sure we all agree
that was a beautiful answer
「どこまで近づけますか」
という質問に対して
to the question, “How Close Can You Be?”
納得のいく答えを得ることができました
And all of us feel close to Jehovah,
私たちは皆エホバを
身近に感じていますが
but what a wonderful encouragement
for us to draw ever closer to him!
もっともっとエホバに
近づきたいと思いました
次に行われる話も
非常に興味深い主題です
The next brother, who’s going to give you
some words of encouragement,
has a very intriguing theme
「アナトテにある畑を
買ってください」です
“Buy a Field in Anathoth.”
奉仕委員会の援助者
Brother Gage Fleegle,
who’s a helper to the Service Committee,
ゲージ･フリーグル兄弟が
話してくださいます
is going to develop this theme
“Buy a Field in Anathoth.”
もう一度主題を言います
「アナトテにある畑を買ってください」
The year was 608 B.C.E.
時は紀元前608年です
The prophet Jeremiah
had already served
預言者エレミヤはすでに40年近く
忠実に奉仕してきました
nearly 40 years faithfully,
and now he “was confined
in the Courtyard of the Guard” in Jerusalem.
今はエルサレムの「『監視の庭』に
拘束され」ています
エルサレムの城壁は
バビロニア人の攻撃を受けています
Jerusalem’s walls
were being battered by the Babylonians.
1年もしないうちに エルサレムは
滅びることになっています
In less than a year,
the entire city
would be completely destroyed.
Jeremiah had to weather the storm.
エレミヤには逃げ場がありません
There was no way out.
There was no place for him to go.
今で言うロックダウンの状態です
He was under lockdown.
Well, have you ever felt like Jeremiah
皆さんも何かの問題にぶつかって
出口が見えないと感じたことはありますか
—as if the world was caving in on you?
重い病気にかかったかもしれません
Maybe it was a serious health scare,
家族が病気になったり
亡くなったりしたかもしれません
the health of a loved one,
the death of a loved one,
コロナのせいで閉じ込められて
いるように感じましたか
or maybe COVID-19
has made you feel boxed in.
Some of our brothers, just like Jeremiah,
have faced persecution or imprisonment,
中にはエレミヤのように迫害されたり
投獄されたりした人たちもいます
and that might be our lot
before the end of this system of things.
私たちもそういう経験を
するかもしれません
Well, what will help you students
ギレアデの生徒の皆さんや
私たち全てにとって
—in fact, all of us—
難しい問題を乗り越える上で
何が助けになるでしょうか
during these critical last days
when we face personal trials, or adversity?
I invite you to open to Jeremiah chapter 32.
ご一緒にエレミヤ 32章を開いて
Let’s consider a dramatic illustration
in the life of Jeremiah.
エレミヤがどんな経験をしたかについて
読んでみましょう
Now, Jeremiah is under lockdown.
エレミヤは閉じ込められています
Jeremiah chapter 32,
エレミヤ 32:6-8です
let’s read verses 6-8:
「エレミヤは言った
“Jeremiah said: ‘The word of Jehovah
has come to me, saying,
『エホバが私に⋯⋯こう言いました
「あなたのおじシャルムの子
ハナムエルが⋯⋯来てこう言う
“‘“Here Hanamel the son of Shallum
your uncle will come to you and say:
『アナトテにある私の畑を
買い取ってほしい
“‘“‘Buy for yourself my field in Anathoth,
because you have the first right
to repurchase it.’”’”
あなたにそれを買い戻す
第1の権利があるからだ』」』
Verse 8 says:
“Hanamel the son of my uncle came to me,
エホバが言った通り⋯⋯ハナムエルが
『監視の庭』にいる私のもとに来て
こう言った
“just as Jehovah had said,
into the Courtyard of the Guard,
『どうか⋯⋯アナトテにある
私の畑を買ってください
“and he said to me:
‘Please buy my field in Anathoth,
あなたには所有する権利と
買い戻す権利があるからです
“‘in the land of Benjamin, for you
have the right to take possession of it
“‘and to repurchase it.
ぜひ買い取ってください』
“Buy it for yourself.’
それで 私はエホバの言葉の
通りだと分かった」
At that I knew that this was
by the word of Jehovah.”
What was Jehovah’s instruction to Jeremiah?
エホバはエレミヤに
畑を買うようにと言いました
Buy a field.
Buy a field?
「畑を買う？どうしてこんな時に」と
思ったかもしれません
Right now, with the Babylonians
beating on the door?
Jeremiah might have thought,
「そんなことより 脱出計画を
知りたい」と思ったでしょうか
‘I need an escape plan, not a field
そもそもアナトテというのは
どこのことでしょう
—of all places, Anathoth?’
Where was Anathoth?
Well, Jeremiah knew exactly where it was
エレミヤにはなじみ深い場所でした
—just a few miles
north-northeast of Jerusalem.
エルサレムの北北東数キロの所です
He was born there into a priestly family.
エレミヤはそこで祭司の家に生まれました
Did he have pleasant memories of his past
in Anathoth as a youth?
子供時代に アナトテで
楽しい日々を送ったんでしょうか
Very likely.
きっとそうでしょう
でもずっと昔のことです
But now that was a distant memory.
More recently, men of Anathoth,
possibly some of Jeremiah’s own relatives,
もっと最近にはアナトテの人たちが
エレミヤの預言に腹を立てて
エレミヤを殺そうとしました
threatened to kill him
because of his prophesying.
エレミヤは複雑な心境だったでしょう
Well, did Jeremiah obey
in spite of any personal feelings
he might have had?
エホバの指示に従うでしょうか
Jeremiah always obeyed,
エレミヤはいつもそうしてきました
even previously when Jehovah told him
not to take a wife or to have children.
妻や子供を持ってはならない
という命令にも従いました
今回はどうするでしょうか
9, 10節です
Well, what did he do in this situation?
Verses 9 and 10:
“So I bought the field in Anathoth
from Hanamel the son of my uncle.
「こうして私は アナトテにある畑を
おじの子ハナムエルから買い
“I weighed out the money to him,
seven shekels and ten silver pieces.
代金として銀10枚と80グラムを量った
それを証書に記し 封印をし
証人たちを立てて
“Then I recorded it in a deed,
affixed the seal,
called in witnesses,
and weighed the money in the scales.”
代金をはかりで量った」
Jeremiah could have worked
in the Legal Department.
法律部門で働けそうですね
Well, he carried out the legal transaction,
エレミヤは適正な取引をしました
the legal requirements of the transaction.
法的な要求に従い
2つの証書を作りました
He recorded the transaction in two deeds
封印されたものとされていないものです
—one sealed, one unsealed—
complete transparency in this situation.
封印されていないものは
誰でも確認できました
Why did Jehovah ask Jeremiah
to buy a field in Anathoth?
エホバはなぜこの畑を
エレミヤに買わせたのでしょうか
エレミヤはすでに強い信仰を
持っていました
Jeremiah already had complete faith that,
yes, Jehovah’s word would be restored
70年が過ぎたら ユダヤ人が故国に戻る
というエホバの約束を信じていました
—when 70 years had transpired,
the Jews would return to their homeland.
But now Jehovah reinforced Jeremiah’s faith
でもエホバは
アナトテの畑を買わせることで
by giving him something specific
to think about.
エレミヤの信仰をさらに強めました
Jeremiah could imagine the time
エレミヤはイスラエルでまた売買が
行われる時を想像できたかもしれません
when buying and selling
would again occur in Israel.
Well, was Jeremiah’s faith
well-placed in Jehovah’s promise?
では エホバの約束は実際に
その通りになったでしょうか なりました
Absolutely.
エズラによると バビロン捕囚から
帰還した最初のグループの中に
Ezra later documented
that 128 men of Anathoth
were among the first group
of those returning from Babylonian exile.
128人のアナトテの人々が
含まれていました
エホバの言葉は必ずその通りになります
Jehovah’s word always comes true.
Well, how might we
—how might you—
では私たちは 皆さんは
アナトテの畑を買いますか
“buy a field in Anathoth”?
実際にアナトテという場所に行って
Well, we’re not expecting you
to go out and purchase
a piece of property
in a place called Anathoth.
土地を買うことについて
言っているのではありません
No.
ではどういうことでしょうか
ヘブライ 11章を見てみましょう
We find a clue, though, in Hebrews chapter 11
—Hebrews 11:1:
11:1です
「信仰とは 望んでいる事柄が
実現するという確信であり
“Faith is the assured expectation
of what is hoped for,
目に見えないものが実在するという⋯⋯
証拠を持っていることです」
the evident demonstration
of realities that are not seen.”
The Simple English Bible {
「簡明な英語聖書」はこう訳しています
「信仰とは 望んでいる事柄の
権利証書である」
“Faith is the title-deed
to the things we hope for.”
Now, most of us in special full-time service,
we don’t own property.
特別全時間奉仕者のほとんどは
土地を持っていません
But we may have the title to a car.
でも車を持っているかもしれません
What does that mean?
その車が自分の物であることを示す
書類を持っているでしょう
That means that car, that vehicle,
belongs to us personally.
信仰は「権利証書」です
Our faith is the “title-deed”
of good things to come,
望んでいる事柄が
必ず実現するという確信です
a guarantee of future realities.
エレミヤには証書がありました
Jeremiah had a “title-deed.”
私たちにも信仰という
「権利証書」があります
We have a “title-deed” of faith.
So how do we “buy a field in Anathoth”?
ではどのように畑を買いますか
It’s not a type-antitype situation;
it’s just an illustration.
これは予型と対型ではなく
単なる例えです
In the context of our discussion,
この話では 畑を買うというのは
it means we exercise faith
in Jehovah’s promises.
エホバの約束に信仰を抱く
という意味です
問題にぶつかるとき
When facing a trial,
we can search Jehovah’s Word
for promises regarding the future,
私たちは聖書から
将来についての約束を探します
and that gives us strength
to keep on enduring.
そうすれば頑張る力が湧いてきます
For example,
if we’re facing a serious illness,
例えば 重い病気にかかっても
聖書には「『私は病気だ』と言う
住民はいなくなる」とあります
God’s Word promises:
“No resident will say: ‘I am sick.’”
家族を亡くすのはつらいことです
If we’re grieving the death of a loved one,
エホバは聖書の中で
復活があると約束しています
the Bible assures us
there is going to be a resurrection.
試練がなくならないとしても
The trial doesn’t disappear yet,
but exercising faith in Jehovah’s promises
エホバの約束に対する信仰があれば
頑張り続けることができます
helps us to endure.
Now, there’s something else that we can learn
エレミヤの経験から
from that dramatic illustration
in the life of Jeremiah.
ほかにもどんなことが学べるでしょうか
Back in Jeremiah 32, notice,
please, verses 13 through 15.
エレミヤ 32:13-15を
読んでみましょう
Jeremiah was inspired to write, he said:
エレミヤはこう言っています
「私は彼らの前でバルクに命じて言った
“I now commanded Baruch
in their presence, saying:
『イスラエルの神 大軍を率いる
エホバはこう言っています
“‘This is what Jehovah of armies,
the God of Israel, says,
「これらの証書 封印された購入証書と
“‘“Take these deeds, this deed of purchase,
“‘“the sealed one
and the other deed left unsealed,
封印されていないもう1つの証書を
土の器に入れなさい
“‘“and put them into an earthenware vessel,
長い間保管するためである」
“‘so that they may be kept for a long time.”
イスラエルの神 大軍を率いる
エホバはこう言っています
“‘For this is what Jehovah of armies,
the God of Israel, says,
「家や畑やブドウ園が 再び
この土地で買われるようになる」』」
“Houses and fields and vineyards
will again be bought in this land.”’”
Jeremiah involved Baruch
in the legal proceedings
エレミヤは畑を買った時の手続きを
バルクに手伝ってもらいました
when he bought the field in Anathoth.
エレミヤの信仰は
Jeremiah’s faith
influenced Baruch for the good.
バルクに良い影響を与えました
We can almost hear
the confidence and conviction in his voice:
エレミヤの確信のこもった声が
聞こえてきます
“This is what Jehovah of armies,
the God of Israel says.”
「イスラエルの神 大軍を率いる
エホバはこう言っています」
Jeremiah used that expression,
「大軍を率いるエホバ」という言葉を
“Jehovah of armies,”
more than any other Bible writer.
聖書で一番多く使っているのは
エレミヤです
It was like Jeremiah said:
エレミヤは言いました
「神はバビロニア人を必ず滅ぼします
‘Our God will certainly overturn
the Babylonians.
‘These promises are real;
you can take them to the bank!
この約束は信頼できます
間違いなく実現するのです」
They’re not counterfeit;
they’re completely true!’
何を学べるでしょうか
What’s the lesson for us?
Our faith can strengthen fellow believers.
私たちの信仰は仲間を力づけます
A sister named Joyce,
while she herself was fighting cancer,
ジョイスという姉妹は
がんになりましたが 闘病中
made what she called shot-in-the-arm cards.
元気が出るカードというのを作りました
They were collections of Bible verses,
姉妹はカードに聖句 出版物の挿絵
pictures from our publications,
歌や「ものみの塔」の記事の
抜粋を載せました
quotes from theocratic songs
or Watchtower {
そして励ましが必要な人に渡しました
and she would give them
to those in need of encouragement.
One of her favorites was Psalm 112:7, 8.
姉妹は特に 詩編 112編の
7, 8節が好きでした
And there it says:
“He will not fear bad news.
こういう聖句です
「悪い知らせを恐れない
“His heart is steadfast, trusting in Jehovah.
揺るぎない心でエホバに頼る
“His heart is unshakable; he is not afraid;
心は揺れ動かず 恐れない
in the end he will look in triumph
on his adversaries.”
最後には敵対者の敗北を見る」
ジョイス姉妹は 悪い知らせを
たくさん聞きました
Sister Joyce had
a lot of bad news in her life,
but her faith in Jehovah’s promises
was powerful.
でもエホバの約束を固く信じていました
Sadly, Joyce lost her fight with cancer
a few years back,
残念ながら姉妹は
数年前に亡くなりました
but she “bought a field in Anathoth,”
でも畑を買いました
復活してエホバの約束の実現を
見ることでしょう
and she will witness
the fulfillment of Jehovah’s promises.
Even now, she’s given us a shot in the arm
今でも姉妹が書いた言葉を読むと
元気がもらえます
—encouragement from Jehovah’s Word—
信仰が強まります
and strengthened us with her faith.
ギレアデの生徒の皆さん
何を学べましたか
And so, dear Gilead students,
what have we learned?
信仰は「権利証書」のようなものです
Faith is like
a “title-deed of things hoped for.”
信仰があれば問題があっても
頑張り続けられます
Faith in Jehovah’s Word
helps us to endure trials and adversity.
Our faith can have
a powerful effect on those around us.
私たちの信仰は周りの人を力づけます
迫害に遭ったら
アナトテにある畑を買ってください
So when faced with persecution,
“buy a field in Anathoth.”
重い病気を抱えたら
アナトテにある畑を買いましょう
When faced with a grievous health problem,
“buy a field in Anathoth.”
When grieving the loss of a loved one,
大切な人を亡くしたときも
そうしてください
And some day soon,
your faith will be rewarded.
皆さんの信仰は間もなく報われます
エホバの言葉が実現する時
畑を買ってよかったと思うことでしょう
You’ll walk in that field
when Jehovah’s word comes true.
Well, what a beautiful talk!
素晴らしいお話でした
皆さんはどうか分かりませんが
Now to be honest
(I don’t know if you are like me),
私はこの「アナトテにある畑を
買ってください」という主題を聞いた時
when I heard the theme
“Buy a Field in Anathoth,”
I thought,
‘Where on earth is he going to take us?’
いったい何の話だろうと思いました
正直そう思いました
I mean, to be quite honest.
フリーグル兄弟 権利証書と結び付けた
Well, Brother Fleegle,
you took us to a very good spot
素晴らしい話をありがとうございました
よく理解できました
with the title deed and seeing
the connection there.
これからこのフレーズ
ちょっとはやりそうですね
And in fact, that’s going to be
a little password.
We might say, “Buy a field in Anathoth.”
「アナトテの畑を買う」
And if we say that to someone
and they looked amazed,
これを誰かに言って
ぽかーんとしていたら
「ああ ギレアデの卒業式
行ってないんですね」と言いましょう
we’ll say, “Oh, you weren’t there
for the graduation program.”
ありがとうございました
Well, thank you very much.
この数カ月間 生徒の皆さんは
Now, for you, dear students,
over the last few months,
教訓者たちと日を追うごとに
親しくなっていったと思います
you’ve drawn very close to the instructors,
and you’ve heard them day in, day out.
来る日も来る日も授業を受けました
いろいろなことを学ぶことが
できたと思います
You’ve learned and experienced
a lot of things from them.
ではこれから 2つの話を
お聞きしましょう
So the next two parts
are the opportunities
for two of these instructors
2人の教訓者が それぞれ皆さんを
励ます話をしてくださいます
to give you
a few final words of encouragement.
まず トレント･リポルド兄弟の
話をお聞きしましょう
So first of all,
we’re going to have Brother Trent Lippold
who’s going to talk to you,
and he has this interesting question:
とても興味をそそる主題です
“Distinguished—By What?”
「エホバが注目するのは？」です
強い人でした
He was a mighty man.
強力な敵を倒しました
He felled the heroes of the enemy.
巨人を打ち倒し ライオンを殺しました
He slayed a giant.
He even killed a lion.
And his name was not David.
その名はダビデ ではありません
誰のことでしょう
Who was he?
Open your Bibles with me, please,
to the book of 1 Chronicles chapter 11
ご一緒に歴代第一 11章を
見てみましょう
歴代第一 11:22からです
—1 Chronicles 11:22:
「エホヤダの子ベナヤは勇敢な人で
“Benaiah the son of Jehoiada
“was a courageous man who performed
カブツェエルで多くの手柄を立てた
“many exploits in Kabzeel.
“He struck down
the two sons of Ariel of Moab,
モアブのアリエルの2人の子を討ち
雪の降るある日
“and he descended into a waterpit
on a snowy day and killed a lion.
貯水穴に下りてライオンを殺した
また 背丈が2メートルを優に超える
エジプト人の巨人も討った
“He also struck down an Egyptian man
of extraordinary size
“—five cubits tall.
そのエジプト人は
機織りが使う巻き棒のように
“Though the Egyptian had a spear in his hand
“like the beam of loom workers,
太いやりを手にしていたが
“he went against him with a rod
ベナヤは棒を持って立ち向かい
“and snatched the spear away
from the Egyptian’s hand
相手の手からやりを
奪い取ってそれで殺した」
and killed him with his own spear.”
He is Benaiah.
ベナヤという人です
Look at all we learn about him
in these verses,
この聖句からベナヤについて
何が分かりますか
the qualities that Benaiah displayed.
ベナヤはどんな人だったのでしょうか
22節には「勇敢な人」とあります
It tells us in verse 22
that he “was a courageous man.”
「カブツェエルで多くの
手柄を立て」ました
He “performed many exploits in Kabzeel.”
カブツェエル
Kabzeel—Kabzeel is a small place
これはユダの南の境界にある
小さな町です
on the very southern border of Judah.
エドムに接していました
It borders Edom in the middle of nowhere.
人里離れた場所です
But Benaiah worked there.
ベナヤはそこで働きました
喜んでそうしました
He was happy to be there.
生まれ故郷だったか あるいはそこに
割り当てられたのでしょう
It may be that that was his home.
Or it may be that that was his assignment.
No matter,
as obscure a place as Kabzeel is,
いずれにしても ベナヤはこの
カブツェエルという所で働いていました
that’s where he worked.
そして聖句にある通り
And the record says that he performed
ベナヤはそこで多くの手柄を立てました
many exploits courageously in Kabzeel.
ライオンを殺しました
勇気がありました
He killed a lion—courage.
But do you notice
that “he descended into a waterpit . . .
聖句によると 「貯水穴に下りて
ライオンを殺し」ました 勇敢でした
and killed a lion”?
Courage.
貯水穴から出てこられるのは
どちらか一方だけです
He descended into a waterpit
with a lion.
There’s only one coming out,
and it was Benaiah.
ベナヤの方でした
ベナヤは「雪の降る⋯⋯日［に］
貯水穴に下りて」いきました
“He descended into a waterpit
on a snowy day.”
He didn’t wait for the sun to shine.
天気になるまで待ちませんでした
その日に殺したのです
He knew that was the day
—adverse conditions, no matter.
逆境をものともしませんでした
下りていって ライオンを殺したのです
Benaiah went in, and he slayed the lion.
23節によると 巨人も倒しました
Look at verse 23,
some more amazing qualities.
He struck down the giant,
‘an Egyptian of extraordinary size.’
「2メートルを⋯⋯超える
エジプト人の巨人」です
But notice this: “Though the Egyptian
had a spear in his hand
「そのエジプト人は
機織りが使う巻き棒のように
太いやりを手にして」いましたが
“like the beam of loom workers,
he [Benaiah]
went against him with a rod”—a rod, a stick.
「ベナヤは棒を持って
立ち向かい」ました
He didn’t have the right equipment
ただの棒です
—courage, adaptability, commitment.
勇敢に
機転を利かせて戦いました
And notice this.
What does he do?
どのようにでしょうか
「棒を持って立ち向かい
It says: “He went against him with a rod
and snatched the spear away
相手の手からやりを奪い取って
from the Egyptian’s hand
and killed him with his own spear.”
それで殺し」ました
機転を利かせ 勇敢に務めを
果たす人でした
Courage, commitment,
adaptability, resourcefulness
良いところがたくさんありました
—these are admirable, beneficial qualities.
でも ベナヤの良い点は
それだけだったでしょうか
Are those the qualities
that distinguished Benaiah?
そうではありません
Not entirely.
There was one quality that exceeded these,
ベナヤには際立って
優れた点がありました
and that quality was loyalty
揺るぎない愛です
エホバから決して離れませんでした
—tenacious adherence
to the person of Jehovah.
聖書を読むと
そのことがよく分かります
That’s what the Bible record reveals
about Benaiah:
どんな時もエホバを支持しました
personal loyalty to Jehovah.
ここで覚えておきたい点があります
There is a caution, though, with loyalty.
The demarcation
エホバを愛していると思っていても
between loyalty to Jehovah
and loyalty to self
実際には自分の方をもっと
愛している場合があります
思い違いをしてしまうのです
can often be blurry.
私たちは 利己的になる傾向があるので
It hides under the inertia
気付かないうちに
そうなってしまうことがあります
of imperfection and selfishness.
エホバを愛しているのか
That line of loyalty to Jehovah
versus loyalty to self
実際には自分を愛しているのか
見分けるのは簡単ではありません
can become very difficult to see.
自分に対する愛は
私たちの中に潜んでいて
In fact, loyalty to self
can lie dormant within us
周りの状況が変化すると
until the circumstances arise and change,
顔を出し 表面化する場合があります
and then it can emerge.
And Benaiah and his contemporaries
ベナヤや当時の人たちの例を調べると
provide for us a beautiful contrast
エホバに対する愛と
自分に対する愛の違いが分かります
in loyalty to Jehovah and loyalty to self.
ベナヤは激動の時代を
生きていました
Think of Benaiah.
He lived in a very tumultuous time.
ダビデは戦士たちと一緒に
逃亡生活を送っていました
David was a fugitive with his mighty men.
One of them likely was Benaiah, among others.
ベナヤはその1人です
These men were comrades in arms
running with David.
苦楽を共にした戦士たちは
実の兄弟のような存在でした
They were a band of brothers.
ダビデに揺るぎない愛を示していました
They were fiercely loyal to David
もちろん エホバのことも
深く愛していました
and, to be sure,
they were loyal to Jehovah as well.
ダビデと一緒にいた戦士たちの中に
For example, among these three mighty men
were three brothers, fleshly brothers.
3人の実の兄弟がいました
They’re mentioned in verses 20 and 26:
20節と26節にある通り
ヨアブとアビシャイとアサエルです
Joab, Abishai, and Asahel.
Now consider when circumstances changed
for the mighty men,
その後 戦士たちを取り巻く
状況が変化します
サウルが死に
when Saul died and David now became king,
ダビデが王になります
in these changing circumstances,
このように状況が変化した時
戦士たちはどうしたでしょうか
what happened to the mighty men?
2人の人 ヨアブとベナヤは
Here’s the contrast: Joab and Benaiah.
全く違う行動を取りました
What happened to Joab?
ヨアブは状況の変化を自分のために
利用しようとしました
Joab saw opportunity
in changing circumstances,
and his loyalty to Jehovah was eclipsed
エホバに対する愛よりも
自分に対する愛の方が
強くなってしまったのです
by his loyalty to himself.
For instance,
その証拠に
ヨアブは権限がないのに
勝手に行動しました
it was Joab who took matters
into his own hands,
and he killed Abner
ダビデが契約を結んでいた
with whom David
had already concluded a covenant.
アブネルを殺したのです
なぜそんなことをしたんでしょうか
He took matters into his own hands.
Why?
He wanted Abner’s job.
アブネルの地位を奪いたかったからです
野望に駆られたヨアブは
His selfish ambitions got the better of him,
エホバよりも自分を
愛するようになってしまいました
and they eclipsed his loyalty to Jehovah.
ヨアブは 勇敢で機転が利く
優秀な戦士でした
Joab was a courageous man.
He was resourceful.
He was adaptable.
Admirable qualities.
でも エホバよりも自分を
愛するようになってしまったので
But in the absence
of deep personal loyalty to Jehovah,
そうした良い点が
台無しになってしまいました
they seem somehow tainted, don’t they?
では ベナヤは同じ状況で
どうしたでしょうか
But consider Benaiah
in the same circumstances.
Benaiah had no part in these kind
of intrigues like Joab and his brothers.
ヨアブやその兄弟たちの
ようなことはしませんでした
エホバに対しても
Benaiah was loyal to Jehovah,
and he was a loyal man
エホバが選んだダビデに対しても
to Jehovah’s anointed one, David.
揺るぎない愛を示しました
24, 25節にはこうあります
And look at what we find in verses 24 and 25,
24, 25節
verses 24 and 25: “These things
Benaiah the son of Jehoiada did,
「エホヤダの子ベナヤは
これらのことを行い
“and he had a reputation
like that of the three mighty warriors.
3勇士のような名声を得た
“Although he was distinguished
even more than the thirty,
彼は30人の人よりも優れてはいたが
“he did not attain to the rank of the three.
3勇士には及ばなかった
However, David appointed him
over his own bodyguard.”
だが ダビデは彼に
自分の護衛をまとめさせた」
ヨアブと同じ状況でしたが
You see, in the same circumstances as Joab,
ベナヤはエホバに対して
Benaiah’s tenacious adherence to Jehovah
揺るぎない愛を抱いていたので
—his deep personal loyalty to Jehovah—
賢く行動することができました
safeguarded him in these circumstances.
ダビデはベナヤのどんな点に
注目したのでしょうか
What did David see in Benaiah?
ダビデは ベナヤが自分と同じものを
大切にしていることを知っていました
David saw in Benaiah
what he himself exemplified,
and that was deep and strong personal loyalty
to Jehovah.
エホバに対する揺るぎない愛です
25節をもう一度見てみましょう
You can see that in this verse,
in verse 25, can’t you?
「だが ダビデは彼に
自分の護衛をまとめさせた」
It says: “However, David appointed him
over his own bodyguard.”
David knew that to assign someone
これは本当に信頼できる人にしか
任せることのできない仕事です
to this very, very trusted position
自分の護衛をまとめる人です
(head of his own bodyguard),
the man in that position,
ダビデは エホバに揺るぎない
愛を示すベナヤなら
if he was loyal to Jehovah,
would be loyal to him.
自分にも揺るぎない愛を
示してくれるだろうと考えました
And that’s what David saw in Benaiah.
数十年後 また状況が変化します
Then came another time of change
decades later.
ダビデが死んで
ソロモンが王になった時です
When David died and Solomon became king
状況が変わりました
—changed circumstances,
another time of opportunity—
またチャンスが訪れました
ベナヤはどうするでしょうか
how would Benaiah react?
The same way he always did:
いつもと変わりません
エホバに揺るぎない愛を示しました
deep personal loyalty to Jehovah.
And it was Solomon when he became king
そしてソロモンは王になった時
who rewarded Benaiah.
ベナヤに報いを与えました
ダビデの子であり エホバから
選ばれたソロモンが
The son of David, Solomon,
Jehovah’s anointed,
rewarded Benaiah for his loyalty.
ベナヤに報いたのです
Turn with me, please, to Proverbs 19:22.
格言 19:22を見てみましょう
You see, Solomon
knew something about loyalty.
ここでソロモンは
揺るぎない愛について書いています
He was the son of David.
ソロモンはダビデの子です
And look at what he wrote about loyalty
at Proverbs 19:22.
格言 19:22を読んでみましょう
「人の美しさはその人の
Solomon said: “The desirable thing in a man
is his loyal love.”
揺るぎない愛である」
エホバが注目するのは
His loyalty
—that’s what Jehovah looks for in us.
ご自分に対する揺るぎない愛です
ベナヤは勇敢な戦士で
So Benaiah was indeed a mighty man,
and he had beautiful qualities.
良い点がたくさんありました
でも一番際立っていたのは何でしょうか
Did they distinguish him?
Not entirely.
エホバに対する揺るぎない愛です
It was his deep personal loyalty to Jehovah
それがベナヤの一番際立った点でした
first and foremost that distinguished him.
ベナヤはエホバを
強く深く愛していたので
And because of that deep personal loyalty
to Jehovah,
those qualities of Benaiah were beautiful.
他の良い点も美しく見えました
では毎日神に祈り
So daily cultivate your loyalty to God
よく学ぶことによって
このような愛を育てましょう
through prayer and study.
That’s been your training here.
ギレアデで学んだ通りです
受けたトレーニングを生かして
Use your training to develop
your close personal loyalty to Jehovah.
エホバへの愛を
いっそう深めてください
That’s what Benaiah did.
Think of Benaiah’s training.
ベナヤはそうしました
どんなトレーニングを受けたでしょうか
He was the son of Jehoiada.
ベナヤはイスラエルの
祭司長の1人である
Jehoiada was
one of the chief Levitical priests in Israel.
エホヤダの子です
剣の使い方ではなく
巻物を学びました
Benaiah was raised with scrolls,
not with swords.
Growing up as the son of a priest,
that was his training.
祭司の子として そのような
トレーニングを受けました
So like Benaiah,
ベナヤに倣い 自分のためではなく
be willing to do the work without the rank.
エホバのために働きましょう
Remember, loyalty is tested
not when you are at ease.
エホバへの愛が試されるのは
順調な時ではなく 難しい状況の時です
Loyalty is tested under adversity.
So be careful in changing circumstances.
状況が変化する時 注意してください
心を守りましょう
Guard your hearts.
この5カ月間 私たちは皆さんの
良い点をたくさん見てきました
Dear students,
you all have beautiful qualities.
We’ve seen them over the last five months.
But may loyalty,
でも一番大切なのは
may your deep personal loyalty to Jehovah,
エホバに揺るぎない愛を
示し続けることです
そういう生き方をしましょう
distinguish you.
リポルド兄弟 ありがとうございました
Thank you very much,
Brother Lippold, for that.
We all felt like we were students
in the Gilead classroom, didn’t we?
私たちみんな ギレアデの
生徒になった気分でした
揺るぎない愛の大切さについて
学ぶことができました
And certainly you helped us
to see the importance of loyalty.
次に話してくださる教訓者は
Well, the next instructor, who’s also
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
教育委員会の援助者
マーク･ヌマール兄弟です
Brother Mark Noumair,
is going to give this stirring encouragement
とても力強い主題の話です
「エホバと一緒に行進してください！」
“March On With Jehovah!”
The young man received his assignment,
若い男性が割り当てを受けます
and it was not for the faint of heart.
勇気が要る割り当てです
He would have to tell
about the desolation of cherished cities,
都市が荒廃することを
伝えなければなりません
the burning of Jehovah’s temple,
and the captivity of his people.
エホバの神殿は焼かれ
民は捕囚にされます
And for delivering these messages
(which they were not easy),
そうしたメッセージを伝えるのは
簡単ではありません
he would endure
人々にばかにされ あざけられ
scathing and murderous attempts on his life.
殺されそうになります
それだけではありません
Now, on top of that,
he would experience
moments of discouragement,
その若者は 時折がっかりし
isolation,
孤独を感じ 自信をなくします
self-doubt.
When receiving his assignment,
this young man said:
この割り当てを受けた時 こう言いました
「エホバ 私にはできません
少年にすぎないからです」
‘Jehovah, I cannot do this.
I’m just a boy.’
出身はアナトテです
The boy was from Anathoth,
and his name was Jeremiah.
名前はエレミヤです
この割り当てを果たす上で
何が助けになったでしょうか
But what would help him
be successful with this assignment?
先ほどのフリーグル兄弟の話にあった通り
It would be following and taking to heart
the very points that Brother Fleegle
brought out about faith.
エレミヤにとって
助けになったのは信仰です
He would need a deep, abiding faith
and trust in Jehovah.
エホバに対する強くて
揺るぎない信仰が必要でした
ほかにも必要なことがありました
And in addition to that,
he would need to learn how to march.
エホバと共に行進することです
エレミヤは戦いの最前線に
加わろうとしていました
Jeremiah was ready to enter
the front lines of the battle
—the battle to defend pure worship
against those who hate it.
清い崇拝を憎む人たちと
戦わなければなりませんでした
And like any good soldier,
でも エレミヤは兵士として
one of the first things you learn
is how to march.
まずどのように行進するかを
学ぶ必要がありました
行進するのはただ歩くより大変なことです
Now, marching is more challenging
than mere walking.
Marching requires determination.
強い意志が求められます
It requires stamina, endurance,
スタミナも必要です 持久力もです
and to keep moving forward
一歩一歩確実に前進しなければなりません
in a regular, steady step.
And as Jeremiah entered this battle,
これから戦うことになっていたエレミヤは
he would need to learn how to march.
行進の仕方を覚える必要がありました
何が役立ったでしょうか
What would help him?
Recalling what was written in God’s Word
centuries before his time,
何百年も前に書かれた
聖書の言葉を思い出すことです
words recorded at Deuteronomy 31:6.
申命記 31:6です
I want to read these words to you.
ご一緒に読んでみましょう
この言葉はエレミヤにとって
とても助けになりました
These words were so important to Jeremiah.
The context was when Moses was encouraging
モーセが民に エホバを信頼するよう
励ましている場面です
confidence in Jehovah.
The nation of Israel was ready
to enter into the Promised Land.
この時イスラエル国民は
約束の地に入ろうとしていました
They would face enemies.
敵たちと戦わなければなりません
They would face a fight, a battle.
モーセは何と言ったでしょうか
But look at what Moses says
in verse 6 of Deuteronomy 31:
申命記 31:6です
「勇気を出し 強くありなさい
“Be courageous and strong.
彼らの前で 恐れたり
おじけづいたりしてはなりません
“Do not be afraid
or struck with terror before them,
“for Jehovah your God
あなたの神エホバが共に進んでいく
［つまり 行進する］からです
“is the one marching with you.
“[He’s marching with you.]
［共に行進してくれます］神はあなたを
見放したり見捨てたりはしません」
He will neither desert you nor abandon you.”
では エホバはどのように
エレミヤと一緒に行進したでしょうか
So how did Jehovah march alongside this boy?
At Jeremiah 1:8,
Jehovah tells Jeremiah:
エレミヤ 1:8で
エホバはエレミヤにこう言いました
“Do not be afraid
because of their appearance,
「彼らの見た目のために恐れてはいけない
『私があなたと共にいて
あなたを救う』」
for ‘I am with you to save you.’”
Don’t be afraid.
恐れないようにと言いました
In other words,
when a person marches with Jehovah,
エホバと一緒に行進するということは
エホバが隣を歩いてくれるということです
you see, Jehovah marches with him,
力を与え 強めてくれます
boosting him along, making him strong.
It’s as if Jehovah told Jeremiah,
エホバはこう言っているかのようでした
‘Don’t worry,
you just come and march with me.’
「心配しなくていい
私と一緒に進めば大丈夫」
And for the next 67 years,
that’s exactly what Jeremiah did
その後の67年間 エレミヤは
エホバに頼り そうし続けました
in Jehovah’s strength.
どうなったでしょうか
エレミヤはエホバから力をもらい
Think about what happened
in Jehovah’s strength.
強情な人々にメッセージを伝えました
Jeremiah preached to hard-hearted people,
including wicked kings,
corrupt priests, apostates.
邪悪な王や祭司 背教者たちにもです
He did it, and as he marched,
エホバが一緒に行進してくれて
いることを知っていました
he saw Jehovah march with him.
そう実感していたのです
He was conscious of that fact.
エレミヤが地下牢に入れられた時
Jehovah saved him
when imprisoned in a dungeon.
エホバはエレミヤを支えました
Jehovah supplied him
a daily ration of food during a famine.
飢饉の間 毎日食べ物を与えました
Jehovah rescued him from a cistern.
水ためから救い出しました
You see, this was real.
実際に助けました
This was tangible.
This was concrete.
本当に助けたのです
作り話ではありません
It wasn’t made-up.
エホバが共に行進していました
エレミヤはエホバの支えを感じました
Jehovah was marching with him.
And as Jeremiah saw Jehovah’s support,
it strengthened him
and it gave him more confidence,
力づけられ 確信が強まりました
and Jehovah marched with him.
エホバと一緒に行進していたので
And then Jeremiah was ready
for the next trial.
次の試練に備えることもできました
この点を取り上げるのはなぜでしょうか
Why do we bring this up?
Because your situation
is very similar to Jeremiah’s.
皆さんはエレミヤと
とても似た状況にいるからです
なぜそう言えるでしょうか
How so?
Along with your Gilead training,
you are being put on the front lines.
ギレアデで訓練を受けた皆さんは
戦いの最前線に向かいます
これまでになかったような仕方で
You’re going to be asked
to defend pure worship,
清い崇拝を擁護しなければ
ならないでしょう
maybe like you never have before.
So we want you to stay in the battle.
戦い続けてください
行進し続けてください
We want you to keep marching.
For example, what if in your assignment,
例えば 割り当てられた場所で
反対が強まって
opposition turns into outright persecution?
迫害が始まったらどうしますか
Or what if in your branch territory,
あるいは 支部の区域で
政情不安や戦争が生じたらどうしますか
you face political upheaval or war?
What if you need
あるいは
ウクライナや周辺の国々の
兄弟たちのように
to risk your lives
to provide relief
命懸けで
like our brothers in and around Ukraine
are doing?
救援活動をしなければならない
状況になったとします どうしますか
What if that happens?
兄弟姉妹は皆さんが
どうするかを見ています
Your brothers will be looking to you
as an example.
Will you be able to set that example?
良い手本を示しますか
ずっと良い手本でいられますか
Can you maintain that example?
もちろんです
Yes, you can.
Because when you march with Jehovah
エホバと一緒に行進するなら
よく聞いてください
—now listen carefully
エホバと一緒に行進するなら
when you march with Jehovah,
he does something very special for you
in moments of weakness.
エホバは あなたが弱っているとき
特別なことをしてくれます
Well, consider what happened to Jeremiah.
エレミヤの例を考えてみましょう
At one point,
it got so bad that he wanted to quit.
エレミヤは ある時弱気になり
もうやめたいと思いました
‘I’m quitting.’
エレミヤ 20:9で
Jeremiah 20:9:
‘I’m not going to mention Jehovah’s name.
「エホバについてもう話さない
ようにしよう」と言っています
‘I’m not going to talk about it anymore.
‘I’m discouraged.
I’m tired.
「がっかりした 疲れた もうエホバと
一緒に行進するのはやめよう」
I’m exhausted.
I’m going to stop marching.’
He was losing his focus.
諦めてしまいそうになりました
エホバはエレミヤを
どのように助けたでしょうか
So how does Jehovah help him?
What did Jehovah do?
Did he say, ‘Well, Jeremiah, that’s it.
こう言いましたか 「疲れてしまったなら
もういいよ 別の預言者を探すから」
If you’re going to be exhausted,
I’ll find another prophet.’
No, Jehovah did not do that.
いいえ そんなことは言いませんでした
では どうしたでしょうか
What did Jehovah do?
しっかり覚えておきたい点です
And this is a thought
we want you to take to heart,
エレミヤ 20:11
Jeremiah 20:11.
How does Jehovah help him to keep marching?
エレミヤをどのように助けたでしょうか
「エホバは恐るべき戦士のように
“But Jehovah was with me
“[like a what, friend?
［友でも兄弟でもありません
“like a brother?
No, no, no.]
恐るべき戦士のように］
私と共にいてくださいました」
like a fearsome warrior.”
So in what way
did Jehovah prove to be a fearsome warrior,
では エホバはどのように恐るべき戦士
a mighty soldier,
standing right at Jeremiah’s side?
強力な兵士のように
エレミヤと共にいたでしょうか
How did Jehovah do that?
何をしたでしょうか
戦いについて考えてみましょう
Well, what happens in battle?
When a soldier sees
a fellow soldier stumble and fall,
兵士が倒れそうになったら
仲間の兵士はどうするでしょうか
what does he do?
すぐに駆け寄ります
腕を回してしっかり支え
He rushes to his side; he supports him;
he grabs him;
they go together;
安全な場所まで一緒に歩いていきます
he wraps his arm around him,
and they move to safety together.
This is what Jehovah did for Jeremiah.
エホバがエレミヤにしたのは
そういうことです
In fact, Jeremiah tells us this
エレミヤはその点について
20:7でこう言っています
in chapter 20, and in verse 7.
What does Jeremiah say?
エレミヤ自身が経験したことです
He experienced this.
こうあります
He says:
「あなたは私に対して
力を振るい 勝ちました」
“You used your strength against me,
and you prevailed.”
「私に対して力を振る」った
どういうことでしょうか
“You used your strength against me.”
What does that mean?
Jehovah used his strength
against Jeremiah’s weakness.
エホバはエレミヤを強めるために
力を使いました
Seeing Jehovah do this for him
エレミヤはエホバに何度も
何度も力づけられたので
time and again, time and again,
自分一人の力では決してできなかった
ことを成し遂げることができました
enabled Jeremiah to accomplish
what he could have never accomplished
on his own.
この点を決して忘れないでください
This is the point we’re making for you.
All of these experiences
strengthen and transform
エレミヤはエホバに力づけられたので
変われました
his natural shyness,
以前は内気で
his feelings of inadequacy,
自分に自信がなく
and his lack of confidence
弱気なところがありましたが
into ironlike boldness.
勇敢な人になりました
Jehovah was with him
like a fearsome warrior.
エホバは 恐るべき戦士のように
エレミヤと共にいて
Jehovah loved the commission
he gave Jeremiah.
エレミヤを支えました
He was working with Jeremiah
to fulfill this commission.
エレミヤが大切な任務を
しっかり果たせるように助けたのです
It was precious to Jehovah.
Just like your commission,
it’s precious to Jehovah.
皆さんにも エホバから与えられた
大切な仕事があります
So you can be assured
that Jehovah is going to do the same for you.
エホバは皆さんのことも助けてくれます
そのことを決して忘れないでください
We want you to have that confidence.
In fact, one sister,
実際ある姉妹は
who not long ago graduated from Gilead,
少し前にギレアデを卒業した姉妹ですが
experienced this firsthand.
そのことを 身をもって経験しました
姉妹は 割り当てられた場所に着いて
間もなく逮捕されました
Shortly after arriving in her assignment,
she was arrested.
Our sister was held captive
in a dungeonlike prison.
そして地下牢のような所に入れられました
And during that time,
she was given meager rations of food
ごくわずかな食べ物しか与えられません
and was subjected
to painful, prolonged punishment.
長い間ひどい扱いを受けます
どうやって耐えたのでしょうか
How was she able to endure?
力を失わないようにするため
どうしたでしょうか
How could she stay strong?
How?
By marching with Jehovah.
エホバと共に行進したのです
And she never lost sight of the fact
that she was part of an army of marchers.
次のことを見失わないようにしました
恐るべき戦士エホバや仲間の兵士と
一緒に行進していることです
She was marching with the fearsome Warrior.
In fact, this is what she said:
姉妹はこう言っています
「ギレアデのクラスメートについて考え
“Thinking about my Gilead classmates
“and visualizing their faces gave me power.
みんなの顔を思い浮かべると
力が湧いてきました
“I kept their smiling faces in front of me.
みんなの笑顔を思い浮かべました
“I imagined where each classmate sat
教室の左から右に
前から後ろに 順々にです
“—each row from left to right—
front to back.
みんながどこから来たか
どんな仕事をしていたかを思い出しました
“I recalled where they were from,
what work they did in their assignments.
時間があっという間に過ぎました
痛みは感じませんでした
“This made the time go by quickly,
and I felt no physical pain at all.
“I sang in my head Kingdom songs.
心の中で王国の歌を歌いました
“The song I sang the most
was ‘Jehovah Is Your Name.’
よく歌ったのは
『あなたの名はエホバ』です
もう1つ力になったのは
“Another song that touched my heart deeply
38番の『神はあなたを
強い人にしてくださる』という歌です
“was song number 38,
‘He Will Make You Strong.’
“I made that song more personal
エホバの愛を実感するために
『あなた』という所を
『私』に置き換えて歌いました
“by replacing the pronoun ‘you’ with ‘me.’
“This song helped me never to give up.
決して諦めない という
決意が強まりました
聖書がなかったので
“I had no Bible.
“So each day, I meditated on Bible teachings
パラダイスでの永遠の命や
復活の希望について毎日思い巡らしました
“such as everlasting life in Paradise
and a resurrection hope.
そうすると 言葉にできないような喜びや
“These meditations gave me deep inner joy
“and a calm that cannot be described.
穏やかな気持ちを感じることができました
“At times, I thought about the possibility
of facing death,
もしかしたら死ぬかもしれないと
思いましたが
そのことばかり考えないよう
but the fear of death did not consume me.”
気持ちを切り替えました」
Yes, she thought about the possibility
of facing death,
姉妹は死ぬかもしれないと思いましたが
そのことばかり考えずに
気持ちを切り替えたのです
but the fear of death did not consume her.
The fearsome Warrior, Jehovah,
was marching with her.
恐るべき戦士エホバが
共に行進していました
No prison walls, no bars
can block Jehovah from marching with her.
刑務所の壁も障害にはなりませんでした
And our sister was recently released
from prison.
うれしいことに 最近
姉妹は釈放されました
私たちは 将来
So whatever your trials,
どんな試練に遭うのかは分かりません
we don’t know
what trials you’re going to face.
You don’t know.
We don’t know.
誰も知りません
But reflect on how Jehovah supports you.
エホバの支えについて思い巡らし
戦い続けましょう
Stay in the battle.
エホバの支えについて思い巡らせば
その支えを実感できます
And when you reflect
on how Jehovah supports you,
it’s tangible, it’s real, it’s concrete.
Think about that.
エホバはずっと一緒に行進してくれます
Jehovah will never stop marching with you.
And remember, you are part of a large army.
皆さんは大きな軍隊の中にいます
1人ではありません
You’re not alone.
Therefore, when you see
a fellow worshipper struggling,
ですから 仲間が大変そうにしているなら
そのままにしないでください
don’t ignore them.
Help them not to fall behind.
倒れないよう助けてください
助けましょう 助けるのです
Help them.
仲間だからです
You’re part of an army.
You’ve been trained to do this.
助ける訓練も受けてきました
この学校で学びました
That’s what school taught you:
ばらばらにではなく 協力して戦います
1人ではなく みんなで戦うのです
not to be independent,
but to be interdependent,
not independen—interdependent
with your brothers and sisters.
兄弟姉妹と一緒に戦うのです
That’s your job.
必要ならすぐに援護し
行進し続けましょう
Be quick to help them back up.
Keep marching with Jehovah.
皆さんは これからどんな問題に
ぶつかるとしても 備えができています
And although you don’t know
what challenges lie ahead,
you are prepared.
So with your marching orders in hand,
ですから 勇気を出し
力強く行進しましょう
be courageous and strong,
試練に遭っても それを乗り越えれば
次の試練に力強く立ち向かえます
knowing that each trial you face,
each trial you endure,
will make you stronger for the next one.
忘れないでください 恐るべき戦士
強力な兵士であるエホバが
Be confident that you will always have
the fearsome Warrior,
the mighty Soldier marching by your side.
いつもあなたと一緒に行進しているのです
He’s there, Jehovah.
では 出掛けてください
So now go
wherever the battle may take you.
問題に立ち向かいましょう
出掛けていって
与えられた仕事を行ってください
Go,
and be determined to fulfill your commission
to support your brothers
兄弟姉妹を支え
as you march on with Jehovah.
エホバと一緒に行進してください
What a powerful encouragement
本当に力強い話でした
—one that I’m sure you’ll remember
for many years to come!
これから何年たっても忘れないでしょう
生徒の皆さんにおわびします
And students, maybe I need to apologize.
アナトテがこんなにはやるとは
思っていませんでした
I didn’t realize Anathoth
was going to be the buzz word.
もし最初から分かっていたなら
話をこう紹介していたと思います
You see, if I had realized that
in the beginning in my introduction,
I would have said,
“We need to follow the example of Jesus,
「マタイ 16:14によると
“who according to Matthew 16:14
人々はイエスがエレミヤだと思いました
people thought was Jeremiah,
who was from Anathoth.”
ちなみに エレミヤは
アナトテ出身です」
But anyway, you can take note of that.
おわびして訂正します
ヌマール兄弟 本当に力強い
But thank you again, Brother Noumair.
That was
a very encouraging and stimulating talk.
励みになる話をありがとうございました
Although these talks
were directed to the Gilead graduates,
ギレアデ卒業生のための話でしたが
私たちみんなに役立つ点が
含まれていましたね
they contain
beneficial lessons for all of us.
パート1を楽しまれましたか
We hope you enjoyed Part 1.
Parts 2 and 3 will be available on jw.org
later this month.
パート2とパート3は
今月後半にアップされます
今月のビデオレターはアメリカからです
Our postcard is from the United States.
It’s a large territory encompassing
a variety of landscapes.
非常に大きな国で
さまざまな景色を楽しめます
There are majestic mountains,
雄大な山々 入り組んだ渓谷
twisting ravines,
熱帯の島々 広大な砂漠があります
tropical islands,
and vast deserts.
Across this varied land
resides an even greater diversity of people.
この国に住む人々は
それ以上に多様性に富んでいます
120万人以上の伝道者が
114の言語で
To help all they can,
over 1.2 million publishers
preach in 114 languages!
そうした人たちに伝道しています
自分の言語であれ 学んだ言語であれ
Whether native speakers
or learners of a new language,
伝道者たちは人々の
心を動かすよう努力しています
publishers try to reach the heart.
アメリカには ハイチ･クレオール語を
話す人たちが大勢います
One of the largest language groups
in the United States is Haitian Creole.
支部の区域には ハイチ系の人が
100万人ほどいます
There are approximately one million people
of Haitian descent in the branch territory
伝道者は1万人以上です
with over 10,000 publishers.
ハイチの人々は快活で
Haitians are a vibrant people as expressed
陽気なダンスやカラフルな衣装で
知られています
in their energetic dances,
their colorful clothing,
食べ物もおいしいです
and their delicious food.
フロリダ州マイアミの北には
Just north of Miami, Florida,
there’s a community referred to
as “Little Haiti.”
「リトル･ハイチ」として知られる
コミュニティがあります ここです
It’s here where the 80 publishers
of the West Haitian Creole Congregation
ハイチ･クレオール語西会衆の
80人の兄弟姉妹が
search for lovers of truth.
真理を愛する人たちを探しています
They have witnessed
in parks and on street corners.
公園でも街路でも伝道しています
They have written letters and focused
手紙で伝道したり 聖書を学んでいる人の
家族に伝道したりしています
on the family members
of their Bible students.
The congregation now
会衆では平均126件の
聖書レッスンが行われています
conducts on average 126 Bible studies!
With love, the brothers and sisters
フロリダ州マイアミの
ハイチ･クレオール語西会衆の
兄弟姉妹が
of the West Haitian Creole Congregation
of Miami, Florida,
世界中の仲間に
愛とあいさつを送っています
send their greetings
to the worldwide brotherhood!
エホバの証人の世界本部から
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting!
JW Broadcastingでした